<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian's compass, or, The mariner's companion being a brief compendium of the principles of religion, in the things which are necessary to be known and practised by all who profess the name of Christ / long since prepared, and now published by John Durant ...</title>
            <author>Durant, John, b. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36938</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2671</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12418055</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12418055</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61766</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36938)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61766)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 378:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian's compass, or, The mariner's companion being a brief compendium of the principles of religion, in the things which are necessary to be known and practised by all who profess the name of Christ / long since prepared, and now published by John Durant ...</title>
                  <author>Durant, John, b. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 92 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.L. for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61766:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CHRISTIAN'S</hi> COMPASS: <hi>OR, The Mariner's</hi> COMPANION.</p>
            <p>BEING A Brief COMPENDIUM of the <hi>Principles of Religion,</hi> in the things which are neceſſary to be <hi>known</hi> and <hi>practiſed</hi> by all who profeſs the Name of CHRIST.</p>
            <p>Long ſince prepared, and now publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>John Durant</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel (ſomtimes in the Navy, and now) at Chriſts Church CANTERBVRY.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 77.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thy way is in the Sea, and thy path in the great waters, and thy footſteps are not known</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. L.</hi> for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. MDCLVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:61766:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61766:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To every Chriſtian (eſpecially e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſea-man)</hi> The Author wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a good Voyage, and as an help therein humbly preſents them with this Card or Compaſs.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear ſouls,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere are many years paſt ſince theſe meditations were firſt conceived; and albeit I have once and again had thoughts of publiſhing them, yet ſtill I have been diverted from theſe thoughts until now. And now they come abroad almoſt in the very ſame dreſs in which they were at firſt. The <hi>notions are the very ſame,</hi> and the matter throughout is not any thing altered, only I have expunged and blotted out ſome more <hi>pedantick phraſes</hi> which ſome of the heads were expreſſed in (according to my then juvenile fancie:) And I account the blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting out of them no blot to the book: Nor the confeſſion thereof any ſhame to my ſelfe. Indeed <hi>the enticing words of mans wiſdome</hi> would have been a great <hi>blemiſh</hi> to the truths of Christ, which are
<pb facs="tcp:61766:3"/>ever moſt <hi>powerful</hi> and glorious, when moſt <hi>plainly</hi> held forth.</p>
            <p>The deſigne was <hi>to ſpiritualize the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations of a Sea-voyage unto ſome ſoul-advantage:</hi> and my thoughts were to have held forth the principal (if not the whole) reſult of my meditations to the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in that ſhip I was (in the year <hi>1642</hi>) as a farewell to them. But our ſuddame parting after wee came to an ancho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Thames, prevented it. Hereupon I veſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſome time or other to print it. For I confeſs I was loath to conceale the things which ſo well pleaſed mee then, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed do yet (if I may with humility ſay any thing of my own pleaſeth me) hoping they may pleaſe and profit ſome others as well as my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And (Reader) whoever thou art, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelfe that thy pains in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of this will be profitable, in caſe thou obſerve thoſe directions.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1. Read with a ſober minde.</hi> Do not <hi>run</hi> from any head as ſoon as thou haſt read it. The things are delivered <hi>briefly,</hi> yet <hi>comprehenſively. A</hi> little medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſerious conſideration, will make ever) <hi>page</hi> ſwell into, yea and exceed a-<hi>ſheet.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:61766:3"/>All who know what belongs to hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Divinity-heads,</hi> know that this ſmall <hi>Manual</hi> might have made a large <hi>volume.</hi> But the truth is, I did induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſhorten and contract it, that I might put thee (Reader) upon an induſtrious and diligent inlargement by meditation and conſideration.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. Commit the whole</hi> (if, and as much as it may be) <hi>unto memory.</hi> That thou mayoſt, if the matter be reduced in a Catechatical way to queſtions &amp; anſwers; as readily anſwer unto, and tell any head in this ſpiritual Compaſs, as our Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners can their Sea-compaſs. For inſtance, Suppoſe one asks you in your heads of knowledge, <hi>What is your firſt point?</hi> Anſwer, It is <hi>God</hi> who ſtands for <hi>North.</hi> And ſuppoſe it be asked in your <hi>heads of practiſe,</hi> What is the <hi>firſt point</hi> of the Compaſs there? <hi>Anſwer, Never ſtir, or ſteer in any courſe but by light from God.</hi> So of the reſt. That is my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond direction. Labour to be as ready in ſaying this, as our cabin-boys are brought to be ready in their compaſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3. Indeavor to improve this by imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations;</hi> eſpecially in the laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations.
<pb facs="tcp:61766:4"/>Men at Sea make many obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations (and ſo may men at land likewiſe) which if they were but ſo wiſe and holy as to improve unto ſome divine meditations, might be very uſeful for practical and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>application</hi> in ſundry ſpiritual caſes.</p>
            <p>Theſe directions I commend to every one, into whoſe hand providence ſhal put this book. But to ſuch as are <hi>Mariners</hi> I have two other words to add, and let me beſeech them to minde and conſider them.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1. The great God is aroſe from his place, and is now upon the waters,</hi> to do great things by thoſe whoſe cry is in the ſhips. <hi>Jehovah</hi> hath mighty works to be done upon the mighty waters; and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are to be his inſtruments for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of many glorious propheſies.</p>
            <p>Therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. Now let every Mariner look out, and look about him.</hi> Happy are they whom God will chuſe, and uſe at all. But more happy are they, who (as the ſhips of Tarſhiſh) <hi>ſhal come firſt, (as Iſa. 60 9.)</hi> As there is glory in being in Chriſt firſt, <hi>(unto which Paul alludes, Rom. 16.7.)</hi> So there is a peculiar priviledge in being uſed by Chriſt firſt in any great ſervice.
<pb facs="tcp:61766:4"/>Seamen therefore, now if ever look after godlineſs. <hi>God hath choſen the godly man for himſelf and ſervice.</hi> Wicked men whom God doth uſe, may and ſhall have large rewards and <hi>good wages,</hi> but yet they ſhal loſe their Voyage. Even <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> had his wages for his ſervice, <hi>(as it is Ezek. 29.18.)</hi> Yet alas! what became of him? <hi>O ye gallant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners</hi> (who are to ſwim and ſerve in gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant ſhips upon a gallant ſervice) ſtrive to be truly <hi>gracious,</hi> which will be your greateſt <hi>gallantry and glory now, and to eternity;</hi> without which you will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be fit for no ſervice (as to God) or for no reward from him (as to a <hi>ſpirituall account</hi>) what ever your works or worth may be from, and as to men upon a <hi>civill ſcore.</hi> O therefore minde your ſouls, and their ſpiritual concernments in all your ſervice! and remember that certainly NOW it's high time to flye from thoſe <hi>Sea-monſters</hi> of Swearing, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Uncleanneſs, &amp;c. NOW its high time to purge your hearts and hands, and to go from thoſe abominations, that yee <hi>may be Veſſels fitted for the Maſters uſe, &amp; prepared unto every good work.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61766:5"/>
            <p>But I'le ſpeak no more unto you at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; yet I'le ſight out the reſt for you in ſecret. Verily (ye Mariners) you have a great place in my heart. My firſt publike ſervice in the Goſpel of Chriſt, was on the Sea; I cannot chooſe therefore but love and pray for Seamen. Let me beſeech you therefore to accept of this ſhort hint in love. Now the bleſsed God (who glorifyes his power in mans weakneſs) glorify himſelf by bleſſing this little book with the furtherance of ſouls in their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Sea-Voyage.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Reader,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am thine (in the ſervice of thy ſoul) for Chriſts ſake and his Goſpels,</hi> John Durant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61766:6"/>
            <head>The Spiritual Sea-man: <hi>OR,</hi> A Manual for Mariners.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Introduction to the Diſcourſe, ſetting forth the state of a Chriſtian in this world, to be as of a Ship at Sea.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Allegory of a Ship,</hi> (as the emblem of our life) as its <hi>ancient</hi> for its <hi>inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſo 'tis <hi>approved</hi> for its <hi>aptneſſe,</hi> and generally <hi>apprehended</hi> for its <hi>plainneſs:</hi> There are but few that are ſo ſlow of conceit, but can eaſily ſee, that like as it is with a <hi>Ship</hi> (laden with ſome rich trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) at <hi>Sea,</hi> in a <hi>dark night,</hi> without
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61766:7"/>
                  <hi>Card</hi> or <hi>Compaſs,</hi> not knowing where the <hi>Haven</hi> lieth unto which it would go, nor how to ſhape or <hi>ſteer</hi> a <hi>courſe</hi> unto it; ſo is it with Mankind ſince the fall: Our <hi>Body</hi> is our <hi>Ship,</hi> our <hi>Soul</hi> is our <hi>rich lading,</hi> (a Pearl indeed of great price, worth more then all the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe of this world) this <hi>world</hi> is the <hi>Sea,</hi> and as we come into it, <hi>naturally,</hi> we want both the knowledge of our <hi>Haven</hi> unto which we ought to bend our courſe; and alſo the knowledge of that by which we might be directed in it. Indeed <hi>Heaven</hi> is our proper <hi>Haven,</hi> there where Chriſt now is, (even <hi>the preſence of God</hi>) called <hi>Heaven it ſelf, Heb.</hi> 9.24. thither we ought to ſteer our courſe. And the <hi>Word and Spirit</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the onely Rule by which we can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to that ſpiritual knowledge where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wee may be able to <hi>ſhape our courſe</hi> ſtraitly and ſafely thither. But alas! naturally we are blind as to both, and our being here is as <hi>in a darke place,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. All the time of our life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather a night <hi>of darkneſs</hi> than a <hi>day</hi> of light. As much therefore as it concerns the <hi>Merchant</hi> to endeavor the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61766:7"/>ſafty of his <hi>Ship,</hi> ſo much doth it concern us to endeavor the ſafety of our <hi>ſoul;</hi> and the way of the one is a fit Embleme of the way of the other, you know that Parable <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.35. where a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian under the ſtate, or in the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the Goſpel, is called or likened unto a <hi>Merchant-man;</hi> ſeeking <hi>goodly</hi> (or precious) <hi>Pearl;</hi> and well he may; for in many particulars a Chriſtian and a Merchant are parallel; or, a <hi>man at ſea,</hi> and a <hi>ſoul</hi> in the world. As to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate this in a word.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Let <hi>this world be eyed as a ſea,</hi> or a place of waters, indeed well it may be, the waters being no more <hi>unſtable</hi> then the world is: there are not more <hi>changes</hi> in the Sea then are in the World, the affairs thereof <hi>rouling up and down</hi> in as great a toſſing as the waves of the ſea do. <hi>Ebbe</hi> and <hi>Flood</hi> are not more certain in the <hi>Waters</hi> then they are in the <hi>World,</hi> by the <hi>flux</hi> and <hi>reflux</hi> of all our worldly affairs; and the ſame <hi>briniſh</hi> taſte, the ſame <hi>ſalt</hi> guſt is in the things of the world, which is in the waters of the Sea. And indeed, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61766:8"/>not uſed to the Sea are not more <hi>Sea-ſick</hi> upon the water then Saints are while in the world: Now are we moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on high, (as to Heaven) anon we are tumbled down (as to Hell.) Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times our way is ſmooth; at other times rough; by which <hi>(as the paſſenger at Sea)</hi> we are continually diſtempered &amp; have conſtant cauſe to long to flee this Sea out of this world.</p>
               <p>Secondly, our <hi>body may well paſs for a ſhip,</hi> which is (in its paſſage upon the waters of this world) <hi>paſſing away as a Ship,</hi> (ſo <hi>Job's</hi> phraſe is:) A great maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie Hull. As liable to <hi>leaks</hi> and <hi>bruiſes</hi> as a ſhip is. And were it not for traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique-ſake for a time, a wiſe Chriſtian would as little care for it, as a Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth for a Ship or bark.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, therefore <hi>it's not it,</hi> viz <hi>our body, but our ſoul, which is our treaſure. Epietet us,</hi> and many of the more refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Heathens then ſaw this, (and ſo ſpake, when they ſaid <hi>the Body was the Organ</hi> (or veſſel) the <hi>Soul was the man and Merchandiſe.</hi> The empty hull of the Ship without Merchandiſe, is of more value then the body without the ſoul.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61766:8"/>
               <p>It's our <hi>ſoul</hi> and its concernments that are our <hi>precious lading;</hi> &amp; of theſe it is alone that we are to fear ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Souls have their <hi>Rocks,</hi> their <hi>Sands,</hi> their <hi>Scylla,</hi> their <hi>Carybdis,</hi> their <hi>Syrenes,</hi> &amp;c. endangering them in this world, as much as ſhips at ſea; <hi>ſins, corruptions, temptations, prophane compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> carnal pleaſures, <hi>earthly-minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> &amp;c. theſe cauſe many to drown <hi>themſelves in perdition,</hi> as it is 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9. Indeed it's the miſery of the moſt, that they either are ignorant of, or wholly negligent in the minding of theſe dangers: They let their Ship run at an adventure, neither conſidering Sands, or Rocks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But 'tis their mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo to do; it ought to be our wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to mind our danger: And all have reaſon to cry out of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en in this reſpect as <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Save me O God out of the waters;</hi> or as it is <hi>Iſal.</hi> 69.1. <hi>For the waters come into my ſoul.</hi> You ſee the ſimilitude will <hi>run</hi> well upon theſe <hi>four</hi> feet, (and indeed many more.) But let this ſuffice to hint it in the general, That <hi>all ſouls are ſea-men;</hi> and that our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61766:9"/>way in the world is as the way of a <hi>Ship in the mighty waters.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <head type="sub">Spiritual Navigation pointed at, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided according to the diviſion of the Body of Divinity.</head>
               <p>SUrely ſith we are <hi>Sea-men,</hi> it's our duty and wiſdom to be skilled in the Art of <hi>Navigation.</hi> How elſe ſhall we be able to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eer our courſe aright,</hi> to ſhape our way ſo as to have a happy voyage.</p>
               <p>Q. But, <hi>How ſhall we learn it?</hi> who ſhall teach it us?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Certainly fleſh and blood cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal this myſtery unto us.</hi> Art may make a Sea-man, but it cannot make a Saint. One may be able to carry a Ship round the world ſafely as a man, and yet not know how to ſteer a few Leagues in his ſoul-voyage without miſcarrying. Men may teach us <hi>artificial,</hi> but they cannot <hi>as meer men</hi> acquaint us with the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſpiritual Navigation. <hi>Humane
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61766:9"/>wiſdom may teach us to carry a Ship to the</hi> Indies, <hi>but it cannot teach us to ſteer our courſe to the Haven of happineſs.</hi> In this matter (as the wiſe <hi>Verulam</hi> ſaid) <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeundum eſt è navicula rationis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> we muſt leave, come out of, yea, deny and depart from the <hi>Bark of Reaſon;</hi> we muſt <hi>lay aſide</hi> (at leaſt not truſt to) the <hi>compaſs of humane wiſdom;</hi> And we muſt to the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> if ever we will learn this <hi>myſtsterie.</hi> He that would <hi>ſteer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to happineſs, muſt have Jacobs ſtaffe, Pauls compaſs,</hi> the ſpirits teaching, and that <hi>annointing</hi> which is from above, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe hee'l ſink into the deep of the bottomleſs pit, and never arrive the fair haven in <hi>Emmanuels</hi> land. In a word; he muſt be an artiſt in <hi>the myſteries of the Kingdom.</hi> He muſt be a <hi>Divine</hi> (for ſo all Saints are) that can be <hi>Pilot</hi> to carry a ſhip, a ſoul to God. <hi>Divinity is the Art of Soul-Navigation.</hi> That alone tells us <hi>which, and where our Haven is;</hi> that acquaints us <hi>how to ſteer aright courſe thereunto.</hi> Now <hi>Divinity</hi> hath been cut out by the Pen-knife of the Schools into three parts, <hi>viz. Speculative, Practical, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Affectionate. Thomas</hi> was for the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61766:10"/>firſt, <hi>Scotus</hi> for the ſecond <hi>Hales</hi> for the third. But a ſound ſerious believer muſt joyn all together. We muſt <hi>know,</hi> and <hi>do,</hi> and <hi>love.</hi> We muſt not divide unleſs we intend to be deſtroyed. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reduce my thoughts to theſe three heads, <hi>viz. Knowledge, Practice, Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and give you <hi>ſhort Rules</hi> (for ſo the Rules of Art ought to be) in theſe things to make up the myſtery of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſoul-navigation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <head type="sub">Things neceſſary to be known by a spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Sea-man, according to the points of his compaſs.</head>
               <p>THE firſt thing which God made was <hi>light.</hi> And the firſt piece of the new Creation is <hi>knowledge.</hi> That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may begin aright, weel begin with this, and ſhew what are the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal things neceſſary to be known by a ſpiritual Sea-man.</p>
               <p>Now ere I proceed, I will premiſe this, That <hi>I ſhall make the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:61766:10"/>compaſs as it were the rule and pattern of my diſcourſe</hi> (which indeed was the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional ground of theſe contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.) And anſwerable to the general points of the compaſs, I ſhall hint ſuch things as I conceive neceſſary to be known and done by a Chriſtian, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the ſteering rightly and ſafely to the bleſſed Port or Haven of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Upon this account I ſhall lay down <hi>four heads of truth to be known,</hi> according unto the principal points of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs; and in alluſion unto them, I ſhall make <hi>God my North, Chriſt my Eaſt, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs my South,</hi> and <hi>Death my Weſt</hi> points. Now the reaſon of this my al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion is this; <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> hath been gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally conceived to be in the midſt of the Earth, and therefore ſome have called it the <hi>Navel</hi> of the World; for as the <hi>Navel</hi> is in the midſt of the body, ſo ſay they, is Jeruſalem in the midſt of the earth. And hence it was that (eſpecially in Scripture-notion and language) <hi>pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have their denomination of ſcituation according as they lay about, or ſtood with reference unto Jeruſalem.</hi> Eying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61766:11"/>
                  <hi>Jeruſalem as our center.</hi> I remember that on the <hi>North-ſide</hi> of it was the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Great King;</hi> on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> the <hi>Mount of Olives, on which Chriſt ſtood when he came at firſt to that City</hi> (and on which he ſhall ſtand when he comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.4.) On the <hi>South-ſide</hi> was Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> called the <hi>Mountain of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi> Pſal. 87.1. And on the <hi>Weſt-ſide</hi> was <hi>Mount Calvery, and the valley of dead mens bones.</hi> Upon this account it is I ſhall make my alluſion to the <hi>North</hi> for <hi>God;</hi> to the <hi>Eaſt</hi> for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> to the <hi>South</hi> for <hi>holineſs;</hi> and to the <hi>Weſt</hi> for <hi>death.</hi> Now there can be no exception againſt this <hi>Allegorical ſpeculation,</hi> as to the handling of the things alluded unto, ſave onely the firſt is not ſo clear, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>the North ſhould be for God.</hi> It's clear e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to any eye, that as to the other three particulars there can be no ground to queſtion their parallelling. But why the <hi>North</hi> ſhould be put (by way of parallel) for <hi>God,</hi> may ſeem not ſo evident.</p>
               <p>To clear that therefore, conſider that of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48 2. <hi>Beautiful for ſcituation; the joy of the whole Earth is Mount Sion;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61766:11"/>on the ſides of the</hi> North, <hi>the city of the great King.</hi> The meaning of which I cannot conceive as ſome do, <hi>viz.</hi> that its ſpake of Mount Sion, as if that were on the North-ſide of Jeruſalem. Our Maps and Geographers ſhew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, (Mount <hi>Sion</hi> being on the South) but I take it thus, that on the <hi>North-ſide of Sion was the city of the great King,</hi> i. e. Jeruſalem, or that part which was called the <hi>City, lay North-ward of Sion,</hi> as <hi>Joſephus</hi> and others atteſt; and ſo when it is ſaid, <hi>The joy of the whole earth is Mount Sion; on the ſides of the North the city of the great King,</hi> the meaning is clear, that the <hi>North ſide of Sion was the city of the great King.</hi> Hence I conceive was that ſpeech of the <hi>pride of Lucifer,</hi> who when he would exalt <hi>his throne above the stars of God,</hi> adds, he <hi>would ſit alſo in the ſides of the North</hi> (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.13.) i. e. <hi>on the ſide which was accounted Gods;</hi> which if it ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the <hi>Mount Moriah,</hi> as ſome do, it ſtill holds with our notion of the Norths being eyed as the place of God; for Moriah was on the North-ſide of Sion, and why may not I harmleſly (at
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61766:12"/>leaſt) collect that <hi>God ſtands for the North,</hi> from that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.6. where promotion is denyed to come from the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> or <hi>South,</hi> or <hi>Weſt;</hi> and without mention of the <hi>North,</hi> it's ſaid to come from God, as if it were a known moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. God put for the <hi>North;</hi> I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preſume, that if I erre in the exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my alluſion, that yet 'tis par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable; and therefore I'le proceed hereupon as I ſaid, to put <hi>North</hi> for <hi>God, Eaſt</hi> for <hi>Chriſt, South</hi> for <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> for <hi>Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Jove principium.</hi> Let's begin there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Mariners do, with our North-point,</hi> i.e. with <hi>God,</hi> ſurely we ſhall not make a proſperous voyage without him, ſith he is the firſt to be known And being wel skilled in this point, we ſhall preſume, and may expect <hi>fair weather</hi> will come out of this <hi>North</hi> (<hi>as the phraſe is,</hi> Job. 37.22.) to make us happy in our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual failing. Concerning <hi>God</hi> therefore, I ſhall lay down theſe particulars as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be known, which I ſhall not expatiate upon, only clearly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly mention.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:61766:12"/>
               <p n="1">1. We muſt know <hi>that God is,</hi> Heb. 11.6. we muſt beware of ſaying with the fool, <hi>there is no God</hi> Creation, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, <hi>even rain and fruitful ſeaſons are his witneſſes A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 14.17. not to mention thoſe grand and undeniable teſtimonies of <hi>ſcriptures</hi> and <hi>conſcience.</hi> But this is the firſt; ſet it in your hearts <hi>that there is a God;</hi> and however Heathens ſpeak of many, yet to us Chriſtians there is but <hi>one God</hi> 1 Cor 8.5, 6</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>We muſt know that this God is the chiefeſt good.</hi> It's onely himſelf and the <hi>light of his countenance</hi> which can make us happy, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 4.6, 7. Bleſſed are they that ſee, <hi>i. e</hi> that enjoy him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.10. Now this is a principle ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be known, <hi>viz. That God is that ſupreme good in the enjoyment of whom all true happineſſe lyes.</hi> All our love and labour to, and for God, depends upon this principle; and the knowledge and belief hereof is of abſolute neceſſity to make us happy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>(Life eternal lying in God, and he being incomprehenſible and unconceivable in eſſence, as being a ſpirit)</hi> We muſt know our beſt way to eye him is in his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61766:13"/>
                  <hi>attributes</hi> (<hi>Exod.</hi> 34.5, 6, 7.) and <hi>works</hi> (as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20.) Eſpecially in his <hi>Son,</hi> (as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.) Read theſe Scriptures, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memember them. Gods Names declare his Nature; his works intimate his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but his Son is the brightneſs of his glory, and the expreſs image of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We muſt know that <hi>as God is a ſpirit,</hi> ſo our onely and chiefeſt way of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, enjoying, ſerving and walking with him, is <hi>in the ſpirit</hi> likewiſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24. As God is, ſo he ought to be known and ſerved. And he being a ſpirit, he is only in a ſaving way known by the light of his own ſpirit, and ſerved in the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and ſtrength of our ſpirits. Theſe four things are the leaſt that we can know in order to happineſs concerning God.</p>
               <p>Concerning our next Cardinal point, <hi>viz. Chriſt</hi> (who is our <hi>ſtar</hi> in the eaſt) I will name no more points in number concerning him neither, but four.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Chriſt is the firſt and clearest light, the true Sun which ariſeth upon the world, by which all are enlightned,</hi> Joh. 1.9. He is our <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> and till he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61766:13"/>there is no healing for us, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.2. He is that <hi>light</hi> which alone makes day, as the Sun in the Eaſt doth, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.78, 79. The whole world lyes in a <hi>Night</hi> of diſmal, damnable darkneſs, until Chriſt as the <hi>Day-ſpring from on high viſite it, to give light to them that fit in darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>God alone is in him reconciling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the world,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.19. We can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be <hi>reconciled, justified, adopted,</hi> &amp;c. but in and by Jeſus Chriſt; and he is made all to us in theſe grand ſoul-ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving matters, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1:30. Chriſt is the <hi>Way</hi> as well as the <hi>Truth;</hi> the way of God to us, as well as the light of God upon us; no man cometh to the Father but by him, as it is <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.6.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt is onely made ours by the union and in-dwelling of himſelf in us through the ſpirit.</hi> It's the ſpirit alone who can annoint our eyes to ſee and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this Sun, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It's the ſpirit who uniteth us to Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. It's the ſpirit who doth fit us for, and bring us to Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where God intends to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to himſelf in his ſon, he there gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61766:14"/>the <hi>Holy Ghost;</hi> none can call <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> Lord but by the ſpirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. How then can any come by him and be <hi>one in Chriſts body,</hi> but by the ſame ſpirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The way of the ſpirit uniting us to Chriſt, is by an act of power on his part; and by an act of faith on our part.</hi> The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit uſes no other grace either to faſten Chriſt on us, or us to Chriſt, but Faith. Believing is the <hi>all,</hi> and the <hi>onely</hi> means of having Chriſt. Other things may prediſpoſe, but faith alone takes hold of, and intitles us to Chriſt. Other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will follow, but not as things joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to Chriſt, but as fruits of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing united unto Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3 16. laſt. &amp; 5.29. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.12, 13. with others.</p>
               <p>As Chriſt is the onely <hi>foundation,</hi> ſo theſe things are <hi>fundamentally neceſſary</hi> to be known of him.</p>
               <p>Now concerning our next point, <hi>viz. holineſs,</hi> which is our <hi>South,</hi> I would fain poſſeſs my ſelf and others with theſe four principles about it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That whoever is in Chriſt, is a new creature,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. which new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61766:14"/>is renewed in <hi>holineſs, Eph</hi> 4.24: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Chriſt in free-grace takes <hi>ſinners when ſinners,</hi> yet <hi>he leaves them not ſo, but makes them Saints or ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fied ones,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.11. This know, Though the unholieſt ſoul <hi>may</hi> have Chriſt, yet none but the holy ſoul <hi>can onely ſay, I have Christ,</hi> though Chriſt did not condemn or caſt off that great ſinner, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.3. yet hee cautions her againſt ſinne, <hi>ver.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p n="2">2: <hi>Holineſs is the ſouls higheſt luſtre,</hi> its the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>South,</hi> at the higheſt: The holy ſoul is in the right and full aſpect of God, as South is towards the North: God is and ſurely we are when we are holy) glorious to holineſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15:11: When we come to perfection in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, then is our Sun at the height in us; and in order unto this we are to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the promiſes, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 7:1:</p>
               <p n="3">3: <hi>Holineſs is Christ filling the ſoul:</hi> As the Sun which paſſeth from Eaſt to South is higheſt in the South; ſo Jeſus Chriſt is at his higheſt in the heart when the heart is moſt holy: A ſoul in the height of holineſs, hath Chriſt in the height in him:</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:61766:15"/>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>This holineſſe is that which is directly oppoſite to ſin:</hi> as the cleareſt light is to the greateſt darkneſs, ſo is holineſs to ſin. <hi>Sin eclipſes holineſs, and holineſs ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſin. Holy</hi> and <hi>undefiled</hi> are all one in Scripture; they are all parallel expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of one and the ſame thing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7: 26: <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11, 14 Our laſt principal point is the <hi>Weſt;</hi> that is, our <hi>night-point,</hi> our <hi>death-principle.</hi> And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it's neceſſary for us to know ſomething of death: <hi>Moſes</hi> propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the thought and ſight of death to Iſrael, as well as life: Now with refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to <hi>death</hi> take four principles.</p>
               <p n="1">1: <hi>Death is certain:</hi> There is none that liveth and ſhall not ſee death: It's the certain <hi>wages of ſin:</hi> men do but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves when they put off the thoughts of death from themſelves, for all muſt dye: The <hi>Sun</hi> of our life will ſet in death: When our dayes come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to this <hi>Weſtern-point,</hi> it will be night, <hi>Heb</hi> 9: 27: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.7, 9:</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>If we dye in our ſins out of Chriſt, we are undone for ever,</hi> Joh. 8: 24: Miſerable are the wiſeſt, the richeſt, the greateſt of men, who cannot dye with Chriſt in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61766:15"/>their arms: As to <hi>dye in Chriſt is gain;</hi> ſo <hi>out of Chriſt it's loſs,</hi> yea the greateſt loſs, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1: 21:</p>
               <p n="3">3: <hi>Death is but the ſouls, or rather the bodyes night:</hi> The ſetting-Sun will riſe again. It's our <hi>benighting to dye;</hi> but it's not our <hi>annihilating:</hi> All, even the worſt ſhall riſe again, and be brought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before Jeſus Chriſt: As the Sun which ſets in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> ſhall riſe in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> So they that go hence by death, ſhall riſe by Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15: <hi>Apoc.</hi> 20: 12:</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>After death comes judgement:</hi> Men that dye ſhall ariſe to be judged either for life or death the ſecond time. Good men ſhall ariſe to life, wicked men to death. <hi>Heb:</hi> 9: 27: <hi>Matth.</hi> 25: Do not ſlight this truth; for it's a <hi>principle</hi> in Religion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6: 2:</p>
               <p>Theſe are things all of them very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be known: As neceſſary as the <hi>four prints in the compaſs,</hi> ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry are theſe four heads, and the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars under them to be known.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not paſſe from this without an addition of ſome other things from the connexion of theſe points in our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Compaſs.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:61766:16"/>
               <p n="1">1: <hi>From the North-point we paſs to the Eaſt.</hi> God paſſeth forth to the world by Chriſt. He comes only down to us by his Son. No man cometh to God but by him; <hi>Joh.</hi> 14: 6: And as ſoon as we have thought of God, it becomes us to paſſe on in our thoughts to Chriſt: For God out of Chriſt is no lightſome nor chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thought: God out of Chriſt is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>From Eaſt we proceed to South:</hi> And indeed, as Chriſt cometh into, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances upon the <hi>ſoul,</hi> ſo <hi>holineſſe</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, even as the <hi>Sun</hi> doth as it riſeth <hi>Southward:</hi> Chriſts paſſage in the ſoul is in the Southern line of holineſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>From South we come to Weſt:</hi> Even the moſt Southern ſanctified Saints that are, muſt paſs on to death: Holineſs <hi>fits</hi> for, but <hi>frees</hi> not from death. The <hi>warmth of Southern</hi> heat (<hi>i e</hi> holineſſe) will enable us to bear the <hi>cold of death</hi> the better; but yet dye we muſt, our holineſs will not keep us from it: To the Weſt we muſt; there the Grave and night of death waits for us all; there our Sun muſt ſet, and our dayes end.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:61766:16"/>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>From the Weſt we come to the North again;</hi> and indeed ſo it is: When we dye we return to God; the ſpirit or every one returns to God, <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 12.7. onely ſome go to him as a <hi>Judge,</hi> others as to a <hi>Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having looked upon the points of our Compaſs in their ordinary connex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, conſider it again in its oppoſition; and remembring ſtill our <hi>North</hi> point is <hi>God;</hi> our <hi>Eaſt Chriſt;</hi> our <hi>South holineſs,</hi> and our <hi>VVeſt death</hi> then conſider and remember theſe things as worthy our noting and knowing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>God and holineſs are things not to be ſevered.</hi> God looks not on any thing in a direct line of approbation, but upon holineſs. Holineſs brings the ſoul into a right light of aſpect and communion with God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Even Chriſt himſelf, as coming into the world for us, muſt dye:</hi> As the Sun which riſes in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> muſt ſet in the <hi>Weſt.</hi> And indeed, that <hi>Christ whoſe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſtar was firſt ſeen in the East of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Did ſet upon the Weſt, when he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the croſs on Calvary,</hi> which was on the Weſt of the holy City.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:61766:17"/>
               <p>The 'firſt of theſe things noted and known, <hi>will teach us to labour and to preſs after holineſs;</hi> to perfect it in the fear and love of God; for without it none ſhall ſee God.</p>
               <p>The ſecond of theſe remembred <hi>will ſweeten death unto us; for why ſhould we fear to follow Chriſt?</hi> Sith he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of death before us, and for us, why ſhould we be ſo loath to dye?</p>
               <p>To help your eye, and thereby to fix theſe things the better, look upon the following Compaſs as an Epitome of this part of our diſcourſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illustration">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:61766:17"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>allegorical compass</figDesc>
                     <p>NORTH <hi>God</hi> He is The ſupreme good Muſt be knowne This by the ſpirit</p>
                     <p>EAST <hi>Chriſt</hi> The light of God The reconciler to God Inioyed by the ſpirit and by faith.</p>
                     <p>SOUTH <hi>Holineſs</hi> Its the new creature The ſoules luſtre Chriſt at height in us Is at enmity with ſin</p>
                     <p>WEST <hi>Death</hi> In is ſelf certain Out of Chriſt ſad ſhall have a reſurrection &amp; brings to iudgment</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">The things or duties neceſſary to be done by Chriſtians, reduced to as many pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Rules as there are points in the Compaſs.</head>
               <p>LET us paſs now from the <hi>ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> part of our Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs (in which we have ſeen the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61766:18"/>grand principles which are neceſſary to be <hi>known</hi>) unto the <hi>practical</hi> part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſee what are the <hi>duties,</hi> or the things which he ought to <hi>do</hi> in order to the arrival to our happineſs. And here I ſhall keep me to my Compaſs, and mention as many points for practiſe as there are noted in our Compaſs, which are thirty two; and for a help to memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I ſhall begin each point with the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial known Letters on the points of our Compaſs.</p>
               <p>Our firſt point is North, which is thus cut out into its eight points,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Never ſtir or ſteer any courſe but by light from God.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">N.</note> Let the Scriptures which are Gods word, be thy <hi>North-Star.</hi> This is the original cauſe of all our miſery and miſcarriage, that we make not Gods commandments our Compaſs: <hi>Thy word is a Lamp unto my feet, and a light unto my pathes,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 105. To the Law, and to the Teſtimony, ſaith Chriſt by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.10. They are the Scriptures which can make us <hi>wiſe unto ſalvation.</hi> I do no more wonder to ſee men ſplit on the Rocks of error, or ſunk in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61766:18"/>ſands of ſin, who caſt off or neglect the Scriptures, then I do to ſee a man make ſhipwrack who wants, or uſeth not his Compaſs. This is the great device of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan (who ſtrives to ſhipwrack our ſouls) in theſe dayes, to make poor creatures diſpute, deny, and depart from the Scriptures. The North Star is not ſo uſeful and neceſſary to the Marriner, as the written word of God unto a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: And he who upon pretence of the <hi>Word within,</hi> doth lay aſide the <hi>word without,</hi> is as a mad Pilot that throws away the <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mpaſs,</hi> that he may ſteer by his <hi>conjecture.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Never enter upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſign but ſuch as tends towards Chriſt.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">N. <hi>&amp; by</hi> E.</note> Let Chriſt be the riſing-<hi>Sun</hi> which thy ſoul doth alwayes <hi>worſhip.</hi> While other men run from <hi>Weſt</hi> to <hi>Eaſt</hi> to gain riches, do thou <hi>lance</hi> forth in no <hi>bottom,</hi> or buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which will not further thee in thy knowledge and en oyment of Chriſt. Chriſt is next to God, and the word of God principally and primarily points at him; <hi>to him gave all the Prophets wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> Act. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3. He that labours for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61766:19"/>things, neglecting Chriſt, is like a <hi>Merchant</hi> that goeth to the <hi>Indies</hi> to fetch <hi>Pebbles,</hi> and in the mean time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets the <hi>pearl of great price;</hi> or like one that digs for dirt, and neglects Gold; ſince 'tis Chriſt alone who is a <hi>precious pearl,</hi> and the <hi>tried Gold,</hi> which can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich our ſouls.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Note nothing enviouſly wch</hi> 
                        <hi>thrives without God;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">N. N. E.</note> indeed nothing can thrive truly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, though ſometimes the wicked (who want him) do ſeem to proſper. Indeed 'tis a great <hi>remora</hi> or hinderance to a ſpiritual Sea-man, to a poor afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Saint, to ſee the <hi>proſperity of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> eſpecially while he is under <hi>adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that it ſhould be ſo fair weather with the ungodly, while it's ſo foul with the godly, hath often perplexed many. It made the Pſalmiſt once think <hi>his Voyage Heaven-ward was in vain,</hi> Pſal. 73.12, 13. but remember not to envy, becauſe of the proſperity of the wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>They make a poor voyage that ſail with never ſo fair a wind, or never ſo ſmooth a ſea, and yet traffick for nothing but ſand or pebles.</hi> He that trades with Jewels; need not envy ſuch at all: Though he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61766:19"/>have <hi>foul weather,</hi> and <hi>rough ſeas,</hi> yet his <hi>Traffick</hi> will make amends for all. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſcarry for not eying this point of the Compaſs; therefore minde it, <hi>Note nothing enviouſly which thrives, or ſeems to proſper, without God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Never Enter upon Notwarrantable courſes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">N. E. &amp; by N.</note> 
                        <hi>to procure any the moſt prized or conceited ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages.</hi> Many a ſoul is caſt away, and ſunk into eternal perdition, by ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring upon unlawful and not-warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſigns, to advance or inrich it ſelf, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9, 10. What got <hi>Achan</hi> by his wedge of Gold? <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7. What got <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hazi</hi> by the <hi>talent of ſilver, and changes of raiments?</hi> 2 Kings 5. Nay, <hi>what ſhall it profit a man to get all the world, and loſe his ſoul?</hi> Any thing got in, or by a non-warranted way, may and will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do the ſoul, though it may <hi>pleaſe</hi> or profit the <hi>body.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Now Entertain the ſacred commands of God,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">N. E.</note> 
                        <hi>if hereafter thou expect the ſoveraign conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God.</hi> Many are willing to have comfort, who care not for command. <hi>My hands will I lift up to thy command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61766:20"/>which I have loved: And I will me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate in thy Statutes,</hi> Pſal. 119.48. Many a ſoul is ready to lift up his hand to take a <hi>comfort,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> wil not ſtretch it forth, or lift it up to take a <hi>command.</hi> But in vain ſhall you cry for, or expect Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts in a <hi>ſtorm,</hi> if you neglect his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands in a <hi>calm.</hi> You who ſwear and drink, and drab aſhore, or in a <hi>calm,</hi> how can you expect God ſhould hear you in a tempeſt? Meditate upon that place, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24 25, 26. He that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth on Land the Lords commands, cannot expect at Sea either a calm or comfort; <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>onah</hi>'s ſin at Land, made a ſtorm at Sea, <hi>Jonah</hi> 1.3, 12.</item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Never eſteem Aegypts treaſures ſo much,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">N. E &amp; by E.</note> 
                        <hi>as for love of them to forſake the people of God.</hi> It was the praiſe of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> that <hi>he choſe rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon.</hi> And he eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the godly's <hi>reproaches</hi> greater ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches then Aegypts <hi>Treaſures;</hi> as it is in that place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26. In this imitate <hi>Moſes,</hi> rather to chuſe to ſuffer perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, diſgrace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the godly, then
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61766:20"/>to injoy the pleaſures of ſin, or to live at eaſe with the wicked. Better is it to go, though a very <hi>boiſtrous voyage, in a poor Veſſel,</hi> with <hi>men,</hi> then to lye upon the <hi>ſhore, though in a brave Country, with wild Beasts.</hi> Better to go to <hi>Heaven</hi> through many <hi>Tempeſts,</hi> and with much hardſhip and fear, then to ſwim to hel with full ſails, and a fair <hi>gale</hi> of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and honors.</item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Erre Not Eſpecially in ſoul-affairs.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">E. N. E.</note> Jam. 1.16. Errors in corporal affairs are not ſo dangerous as in ſoul-affairs. That ſoul which <hi>errs in faith; in love, in holineſſe, &amp;c.</hi> makes the worſt of <hi>ſhipwracks;</hi> remember thoſe <hi>floating marks</hi> (which are ſet as ſo many <hi>boyes</hi> o're dangerous Sands) I mean <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneus, Alexander,</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.19, 20. &amp; 2 Tim. 2.18 <hi>Erroneous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are but bad Pilots;</hi> and he that errs in the matters of his ſoul will make but a hard Voyage, though at laſt his Ship come into the Haven ſale, their ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be as through fire, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15.</item>
                     <item>8. <hi>Eſchew Nothing but ſin.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">E. &amp; by N.</note> He that will ever do
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61766:21"/>good upon a <hi>ſoul-voyage,</hi> muſt fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſin, I <hi>Pet</hi> 3.11. <hi>Job</hi> was a good <hi>ſteerſman</hi> who <hi>eſchewed</hi> nothing but what was <hi>evil,</hi> Job 1.7, 8 He did <hi>not fear a greas multitude, neither did the contem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t of familyes terrifie him,</hi> Job 31.34. Men that will be ſpiritual <hi>Sailors,</hi> muſt fear no <hi>wind</hi> or <hi>weather,</hi> ſin only, <hi>ſin</hi> (and that <hi>becauſe it provokes God</hi>) is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red It's not a <hi>whiſtling Maſte,</hi> not a <hi>ratling Pum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>; not a Lee-ſhore;</hi> not a <hi>ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or <hi>leaky ſhip,</hi> (which are the great evils deprecated and prayed againſt in the <hi>Sea-mans verbal Letany</hi>) It's not, I ſay, any, or all of this that can hurt or hazard our eternal ſpiritual traffique; It is nothing but <hi>ſin</hi> which alone can ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard our ſoul. He that fears and flyes from ſin, ſhall never need fear to ſink or miſcarry: He that is freed from ſin, will ſave his <hi>Merchandize</hi> though he ſhould loſe his <hi>Veſſel:</hi> His <hi>ſoul</hi> wil come <hi>ſafe to ſhore,</hi> though his body ſhould <hi>ſink at Sea.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:61766:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <head type="sub">The ſecond ſort of duties, being the ſecond quarter of the practical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe.</head>
               <p>WE have paſſed through the firſt quarter of our Compaſs, and all the Rules in it are <hi>negative.</hi> When therefore you come upon the breaking of thoſe rules or cautions, or <hi>neer</hi> to tranſgreſs any of them, think you heard Chriſt ſaying, <hi>Beware, come not near.</hi> I ſhall now proceed unto our next quarter, our <hi>Eaſtern,</hi> and <hi>therein</hi> alſo give forth eight points, beginning each with the cardinal Letters.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Eſtabliſh thy heart with grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">E.</note> Heb. 13.9. It's grace which is our beſt <hi>ballaſt.</hi> Opinions, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Expreſſions, Gifts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all theſe, none of theſe can eſtabliſh us. This makes many to be as <hi>boats toſſed up and down with every wind of Doctrine,</hi> becauſe they are not eſtabliſhed with grace. The <hi>heart which is ſerious</hi> and eſtabliſhed with Grace, is like a <hi>ſhip well ballanced</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:61766:22"/>at Sea, it makes <hi>fair weather</hi> (as we ſay) <hi>with any wind.</hi> How many toſſing, tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, rowling, unſteady ſouls do we ſee in this tempeſtuous age, <hi>moved with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wind,</hi> and almoſt <hi>over-ſet with every wave,</hi> for want of being ſolidly and groundedly eſtabliſhed with Grace? Mind this therefore as a principal point of your Compaſs, <hi>viz. Establiſhment,</hi> and that of the heart (not of the head) with <hi>grace.</hi> The moſt gracious ſouls are the beſt Sailors</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Eye Sanctity in every action.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">E. &amp; by S.</note> Let this be thy great ſtudy, to be <hi>holy in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of converſation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.15: While others talk of a <hi>ſaving Voyage,</hi> talk thou of a <hi>ſacred:</hi> Let every piece and part of the <hi>tackling</hi> which is about thy Ship be ſacred. Why ſhould not our Ropes and Sails have on them as well <hi>holineſſe to the Lord,</hi> as the <hi>Bridles or Bells of the Horſes</hi> ſpoke of in <hi>Zach.</hi> 14 20 If you know whither you are ſailing, (<hi>viz.</hi> for happineſs) you cannot forget holineſs. You are ſailing for the <hi>Holy Land;</hi> and what ſhould you eye but <hi>holineſs?</hi> The <hi>white clifts of Sanctity and holineſſe,</hi> lye
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61766:22"/>along the <hi>Coaſt</hi> of the Country where unto you are ſailing. Eye therefore that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te, and when you ſee the <hi>dark clifts</hi> of ſin, ſay, This is not the <hi>ſhore</hi> that I ſail unto.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Ever Strive Earneſtly to live under,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">E.S E.</note> 
                  <hi>and to improve the means of Grace.</hi> Where <hi>Paul</hi> doth plant, and <hi>Apollo</hi> water; where the word of God is preached in <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> and out of <hi>ſeaſon;</hi> where the Scriptures of truth are clearly opened, and rightly divided, there love to live and be. <hi>If thou canst not be on ſhore where preaching is, labor to procure preaching with thee at Sea.</hi> Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our Chriſtian Ship, and for our <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Sea-affairs,</hi> godly <hi>ſpiritual prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> are the beſt and moſt needful Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Suffer Every Evil of puniſhment or ſorrow,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. E. &amp; by E.</note> 
                  <hi>rather then leave the wayes of Christ and Grace.</hi> As you ſhould rather chooſe ſufferings then not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon Chriſts wayes; ſo you muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to endure, that is, to continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any <hi>evil of puniſhment from men</hi> for owning, rather then to <hi>finne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt CHRIST</hi> in forſaking of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61766:23"/>him and his wayes. Account no ſtorm or tempeſt too ſore or trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom to undergo, that thou mayeſt paſſe on in thy Voyage to Chriſt. <hi>Sea-men mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> not fear ſtorms, nor ſhrink back for foul weather.</hi> Nor muſt Chriſtians fear perſecutions. Sometimes troubles are like ſtrong <hi>gales of wind,</hi> which drive the <hi>ſhip</hi> of the ſoul the <hi>faſter</hi> to its <hi>port,</hi> and keep it ſteadier it its way and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Sigh Earneſtly for more enjoyments of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. E.</note> Reſt not in a little, but pant after a great deal of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Though a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Chriſt be very ſweet, yet we ſhould not count it ſufficient.</hi> Out of his fulneſs ſtill ſtrive for a ſupply, even till thou haſt <hi>grace for grace,</hi> i.e. Every grace of Chriſt in thee, anſwerable to what it is in him. As <hi>little of the creature,</hi> and <hi>as much of Chriſt</hi> as may be.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Seek Evermore for ſome evidences of Chriſt in you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S.E. &amp; by S.</note> 
                  <hi>the hope of glory.</hi> Let it not content thee to <hi>make out after Chriſt;</hi> but ſtrive to be ſure thou haſt <hi>attained unto him.</hi> Many never come
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61766:23"/>to good and <hi>grounded hope;</hi> few come to <hi>ſure earneſts</hi> of Chriſts ir-being in them. But look thou to <hi>ſee Chriſt dwelling in thy heart by faith;</hi> Chriſt evidencing his abode in thy ſoul by the evidence of his ſpirit. Be not if it be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ible, alwaies at a venture, or peradve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> for Chriſt, but go to the <hi>aſſuring-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> to make ſure that Chriſt is in thee of a truth. Though to go to the <hi>Aſſurance-Office</hi> for a <hi>Venture at Sea,</hi> is accounted by ſome an underly way of <hi>Merchandize,</hi> yet it's a good way, and very noble in Chriſtianity. Indeed they are the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt <hi>ſpiritual Merchants</hi> that are moſt and deepeſt in aſſurance. The clearer our aſſurance is the more comfortable out voyage will be.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Still Set Eternity before you in regard of enjoying of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S.S. E.</note> To be <hi>ever with the Lord,</hi> let that ſtill ſound in thy ears, and be in thy eyes. Entreat Chriſt not to tarry with thee a <hi>few dayes,</hi> but covet to have him with thee <hi>alwayes,</hi> even all thy <hi>voyage</hi> on earth, and at thy <hi>Port</hi> at death. Let Chriſt be in thy eye both in life and death; Or if thou canſt not be ſo happy as to have
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61766:24"/>his <hi>ſenſible preſence</hi> all the voyage in the time of life; Be ſure thou make it thy deſire and deſign to have him for ever after <hi>death.</hi> If Chriſt will have you put out to Sea, (as his diſciples) and tell you hee'l come after; Intreat him not to fail in that; thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> you have not his viſible preſence no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, yet deſire of him to vouchſafe to you hereafter, to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with him <hi>where he is,</hi> as <hi>John</hi> 17.24.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Settle it Ever in your ſoul as a principle which you will never depart from,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. &amp; by E.</note> 
                  <hi>that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is in Chriſt.</hi> South is by Eaſt, and holineſs is by Chriſt. Chriſt was holy when a <hi>child;</hi> and holineſſe is as near to him as himſelf is to himſelf; it's his <hi>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence;</hi> and therefore abominate all looſe and lewd principles which would <hi>ſet up Chriſt without holineſſe,</hi> and poſſeſs or perſwade thee that thou mayeſt have Chriſt though thou mind not holineſſe; or which <hi>would exalt holyneſſe without Chriſt;</hi> and perſwade, that even <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Reaſon, Education, Morality,</hi> can make thee holy enough to enjoy God, though thou never hear of, nor know
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61766:24"/>Jeſus Chriſt. Let <hi>Ranters</hi> and <hi>Socinians</hi> keep thoſe poyſons to themſelves. Be thou for <hi>Chriſt and Holyneſſe, for Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Chriſt,</hi> ſtill <hi>together,</hi> never <hi>aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> in points or practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">The chird quarter of the duties in the Chriſtian Compaſſe.</head>
               <p>HAving paſt two parts of our Compaſs, wee'l haſten over the other two; onely let me intreat you to mind and con theſe well, e're you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to learn the other. But when you have <hi>got by heart,</hi> or rather <hi>into the heart</hi> this half, then proceed unto the next, which is our <hi>Southern quarter,</hi> and here remember your eight points like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Set thy ſelf alwayes as before the Lord:</hi> Imagine <hi>nay believe it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S.</note> thou art alwayes as directly before the Lord, as the <hi>South</hi> is juſt in a ſtrait line before, or in the face of the <hi>North: I have ſet the Lord alwayes before me; he is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61766:25"/>at my right hand, I ſhall not be moved:</hi> 'Twas the ſaying of <hi>David,</hi> Pſal 16.8. nay, of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was <hi>David</hi>'s Lord and ours, as it's clear by <hi>Act</hi> 2.25. This is the nature and life of holineſs, to eye God alwayes; without holineſs we ſhall never ſee God here, nor hereafter; And tis holineſs which fixes our ſight upon God. <hi>The Southern Sun doth not more directly caſt his beams upon the North, then the ſanctified ſoul doth caſt his eyes, and every glance of his ſoul upon God.</hi> It's the height of thy ſoul, the <hi>Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an point of thy piety</hi> always to have thy face and thy heart toward thy God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>See weakneſs haſtening thee to death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. &amp; by W.</note> 
                  <hi>even when thou art at higheſt pitch or point.</hi> Even the Sun at the height in the <hi>South,</hi> moves immediately to the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and its firſt differenced motion from <hi>South,</hi> is by <hi>Weſt.</hi> You remember in our points of knowledge, chap. 3. I termed <hi>Weſt our death point,</hi> &amp; <hi>South our holineſs point,</hi> &amp;c. Now it's in alluſion to that notion that I make this my ſecond practical Rule in this quarter of our Compaſs. Even ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men at, and in the height of holineſs
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61766:25"/>are by death. <hi>It's appointed for all once to dye.</hi> As ſin hath brought death upon all, ſo holineſs doth not exempt any, I mean death natural. 'Tis true, in a <hi>ſpiritual divine ſenſe, Saints do not, ſhall not, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dye;</hi> but in a litteral humane ſenſe, even the higheſt Saints that have come up to higheſt degrees of Sanctity, have and muſt drink of deaths cup; and it's much for the advance and ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of holineſs in our hearts, to ſee our ſelves alwayes ſtepping towards the grave, going to ſet in the point or place of death.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>See Sin (which is the ſting of death) as taken out,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. S. W.</note> 
                  <hi>and away by Chriſt, if ever you expect to dye in peace.</hi> Often mind, and think up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55, 56. and ſearch thy ſoul, to ſee whether upon good ground thou canſt ſay, <hi>Oh death, where is thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing!</hi> It's not <hi>ſword,</hi> or <hi>plague,</hi> or <hi>devouring Monſters at Sea</hi> or <hi>Land,</hi> which can make death <hi>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nging,</hi> if the ſoul can ſee the bloo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Jeſus to have cleanſed it from all its ſins; <hi>Death onely ſtings with poyſon and pain ſuch as live and dye in their ſins.</hi> But to ſouls who
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61766:26"/>are true believers, who are waſhed with the blood of Jeſus, death is a Bee ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving much hony, but no ſting at all.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Store up Wiſely Some proviſions every day for your dying day.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. W. &amp; by S.</note> Dying men need <hi>cordials,</hi> and ſo do dying Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſearch and lay up <hi>promiſes;</hi> ſtudy and ſtore up <hi>experiences;</hi> How will you be able to ſee ſin as gone, except you be acquainred with <hi>ſin-pardoning-promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and except you have eyes, and taken notice of <hi>divine experiences?</hi> Mark how, and by what God at any time ſpeaks <hi>peace to your ſoul in the blood of Jeſus.</hi> Treaſure up every hint and intimation of <hi>Grace and Glory,</hi> which at any <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> in any duty, upon, or after any <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger</hi> &amp; deliverance (which thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt had) the Lord hath ſweetly given in unto thy ſoul. Oh what <hi>reviving com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts,</hi> what <hi>conſcience-cordials</hi> unto a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoul are the <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>memembrances of ſuch &amp; ſuch diſcoveries and taſts of God</hi> at ſuch and ſuch a time! Verily the <hi>experienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of our life</hi> are often <hi>cho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce refreſhings</hi> in, or at our death.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:61766:26"/>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Set Worldly things under your feet before death come to look you in the face;</hi> Its the <hi>world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. W.</note> and the things of it, which next to <hi>ſin,</hi> makes death <hi>bitter:</hi> We therefore fear to dye, becauſe we are loath to leave the world: houſes, trades, lands, relations <hi>&amp;c.</hi> make the thoughts of death dreadful; where as were we weaned from thoſe, we ſhould with much eaſe &amp; quiet of mind, be willing to go down to the grave.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Still wait and ſtand upon your watch with loynes girded,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. W. &amp; by W.</note> 
                  <hi>and Lamps trimmed:</hi> Be not ſo <hi>mad as the fooliſh Virgins,</hi> to have a Lmp without oyle; nor ſo <hi>fooliſh as the wiſe</hi> were, to ſlumber, and let your Lamps be untrim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; But ſee your Lamp be ready, your oile prepared, and <hi>you your ſelves as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe, waking, watchful, ready ſervants,</hi> who upon any call or knock can go out to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to your Lord, and to meet your bridegroom: ſtudy Chriſts words, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.35.36, 37. and practice his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel which he there gives in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:61766:27"/>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Weigh Soul-works, and all,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">W.S.W.</note> 
                  <hi>in the Ballance of the Sanctuary,</hi> leſt when thou come to be weighed at the night of death, thou be found to have deceived thy ſelf, and be too light. Many never put their ſoul into the <hi>Ballance,</hi> to ſee whether or no that be not as <hi>Belſhazar,</hi> found <hi>wanting,</hi> and <hi>too light.</hi> Others ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver weigh their <hi>works,</hi> or <hi>words,</hi> &amp;c. but do thou <hi>try all by weight,</hi> allowing <hi>grains</hi> for infirmity (which God permits.) Certainly it will be a dreadful word if it be ſaid to thee in the night, Thou art to dye, (as it was ſaid to <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> in his) <hi>Thou art weighed, and found too light:</hi> Judge thy ſelf by <hi>Gods weights;</hi> his weights are <hi>internals, ſincerityes, Chriſts Righteouſneſſe;</hi> but <hi>word</hi> weigh nothing with God, <hi>pretences, ſemblances</hi> are too <hi>light</hi> with him; all <hi>mans righteouſneſſe</hi> in his <hi>ballance,</hi> weigh not as <hi>the duſt of the ballance;</hi> God loves truth in the inward parts, and they alone hold weight in his <hi>Ballance,</hi> that are found in his Sons Robes.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Wind thy ſoul about Christs neck,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">W &amp; by S.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſo thou
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61766:27"/>mayeſt dye in peace. Simeon</hi> with Chriſt in his arms, could ſing and dye, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.29. Though the Papiſts hang about a Crucifix (as many of them have done) yet I am confident it hath been rather a hinderance than a help to them: <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition cannot be a ſolid comfort:</hi> yet Chriſt embraced by faith, and hugged with delight, makes death very pleaſant. The Sun never ſet clearer in the faireſt even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when it came to its <hi>Western</hi> point, then the ſoul can, and doth, when it lyes down with Chriſt in his arms, and goes with him as it were in his boſom to his burial.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">The laſt quarter of a Christians practice, according to his Compaſſe.</head>
               <p>I Have thus run over three quarters of my Compaſs, I muſt now finiſh the fourth; yet I deſire my Reader to ſtay, and to proceed no further till he hath well learnt the former. The points of our Chriſtian Compaſs are not ſo
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61766:31"/>ſoon learnt as our Sea-Compaſs is.</p>
               <p>But yet to finiſh this, I ſhall menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and pray mind well theſe eight points of our laſt quarter.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Whatſoever thy condition be in this world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">W.</note> 
                  <hi>eye God as the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of it, and therein be contented.</hi> Phil. 4.11. The turbulent Sea is not ſo reſtleſs as the diſcontented mind of man. Man under diſcontent <hi>foams</hi> and <hi>rages,</hi> and caſts up nothing but mire &amp; filth, whereas the contented ſoul ſails alwayes as in <hi>ſmooth</hi> waters, and makes all <hi>fair weather within,</hi> even then when it is <hi>fouleſt without.</hi> Did diſcontented ſouls but know &amp; remember how much they diſhonor God by not reſting in that which his providence brings upon them; and how great enemies they are to themſelves in fretting againſt, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that which they cannot help, they would then wholly ceaſe from their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, and ſtrive to reſt in the will of God. <hi>A contented mind may well be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and counted a Kingdom, for it hath much of the Kingdom of God in it.</hi> he hath learned much in ſpiritual practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Navigation, that hath learned with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61766:31"/>
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> in all things to be content. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly godlineſs with content is great gain, Indeed godlineſs teacheth us to be content in all eſtates, whether we get or loſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Wale Not according to the courſe of the moſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">W. &amp; by N.</note> 
                  <hi>but after the example of the beſt.</hi> The moſt are the worſt; and the beſt are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the feweſt: the <hi>broad way of the multitude</hi> leads to death; whereas the <hi>narrow of the few</hi> (that walk wiſely) leads to life. Indeed it's not eaſie to find out the narrow path or life and peace. The broad way of death is open and obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to every eye, as the vaſt <hi>Ocean</hi> is to every one at Sea; but the narrow way, like the <hi>channel</hi> at the end or entrance of ſome Iſle (as it's with ours in the Weſt) is hard to be diſcerned and to find out. It's thy wiſdom to ſtudy to know exactly the narrow way which the feweſt find, in which thou mayeſt ſafely arrive the Haven of happineſs, and not to rowle up and down the broad Sea of the wide world with the multitude, and ſo periſh without any comfort, albeit with many companions.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:61766:28"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Weigh not what men ſpeak or think of thee,<note place="margin">W.N.W.</note> ſo God approve thee.</hi> Not he who commendeth himſelf is approved, <hi>but whom the Lord commendeth,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.18. Neither is he a <hi>Jew which is onely outwardly; neither is that circumciſion which is outward in the fleſh; but he is a Jew which is one inwardly; and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion is that of the heart, in the ſpirit, and not in the Letter, whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God,</hi> Rom. 2.28, 29 It's the madneſs and miſery of many they mind <hi>man</hi> more then <hi>God;</hi> and ſo they may be well reputed of, and reported by men, they are not conſciencious, nor careful of their carriage towards God. But be not deceived, <hi>God is not mooved;</hi> he knoweth what is in men, and at the laſt day <hi>we ſhall be judged according to Gods Law, and not according to mans judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And he that ſtudies to approve himſelf to God, will be ſeen to have been wiſeſt in that day.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Never wink at ſmall ſins,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">N.W. &amp; by W.</note> 
                  <hi>nor neglect little dutyes.</hi> Indeed, <hi>no command of the great God is little;</hi> nor
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61766:28"/>is <hi>any ſin against him little.</hi> But <hi>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively</hi> we ſay (and that aright) that ſome ſins and duties are ſmall. An <hi>idle word</hi> is a ſmall ſin in compariſon of an <hi>oath;</hi> and <hi>profeſſion</hi> is a little duty, if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>doing</hi> or <hi>ſuffering</hi> for the Name of Chriſt. Yet beware of little things in Religion. <hi>A ſmall leak, if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected, may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nk a ſhip;</hi> And a little ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence in looking out at Sea, may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger all unawares; walk therefore <hi>circumſpectly, Eph</hi> 5.15. <hi>Ste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r to a hairs breadth in duty, and flye from the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of evil;</hi> make conſcience of the ſmalleſt duty to do it, and of the leaſt ſin to avoid it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Never wiſh raſhly for death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">N.W.</note> 
                  <hi>nor love life too inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately.</hi> Call not for death before its time, neither hanker thou after life when thy time of death is come. <hi>Jonah</hi> did evil to wiſh to dye, <hi>Jon.</hi> 4.3. Men in a pet, under a pain, upon ſome croſs or trouble, are too apt to cry out, <hi>O that they were dead!</hi> Poor ſouls! they know not what they ſay. Are they fit for that which they ſo frowardly wiſh for? what if death ſhould come at I wiſh, would
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61766:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:61766:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:61766:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:61766:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:61766:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:61766:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:61766:33"/>not they cry out, <hi>Lord take it away?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware therefore of this diſtemper; <hi>Thy times are in Gods hand:</hi> he hath number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them; neither ſubſtract nor add un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods number, if God will have them <hi>many,</hi> do not wiſh them <hi>few;</hi> and if God will have them <hi>ſhort,</hi> do not deſire them <hi>long.</hi> Conſider, he is <hi>wiſe,</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>ſupreme,</hi> and knows what is beſt, <hi>neither can any reſiſt his will,</hi> to lengthen or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the dayes which he hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minedus. O learn to live and to dye in his will!</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Now work wiſely ere Night come;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">N. W. &amp; by N.</note> while you have the light and life, walk in it, <hi>before the night comes when none can work,</hi> Joh. 12.35, 36. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not, nor put off the great things of <hi>eternal life,</hi> unto the uncertain time of thy <hi>natural death.</hi> How many are gone down to the place of the ſecond death, by putting off repentance and faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> till their death came, when they had not ſpace nor grace to do either, and ſo periſhed for ever for the <hi>defect</hi> of that which they did <hi>defer.</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber therefore the wiſe counſel of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61766:33"/>Whatſoever thy hand findeth to do do it</hi> (defer not; ſtay not, but) <hi>do it with thy might: for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wiſdom in the grave whither thou goeſt,</hi> Eccl. 9.10. The ſoul who puts off his great work till the laſt, may dye ere he hath begun to do that which he can never ſufficiently do, ſhould he work all his dayes. Take the preſent time for every work which God by his word, Spirit, Providence, or any other way doth call thee unto.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Name Nothing when thou pleadeſt with God for thy ſoul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">N. N. W.</note> 
                  <hi>but Chriſt and free Grace.</hi> Prayer is and ought to be thy ſtanding daily <hi>work,</hi> and Chriſt and free Grace ought to be thy conſtant <hi>argument</hi> in thy prayers: whatever thou wiſheſt or wouldſt have of God, ſay as <hi>Daniel, Do it for the Lords ſake,</hi> Dan. 9.17. Caſt thy deſires, thy hopes, thy ſoul, and all, <hi>upon the merits of a dying Chriſt, and upon the tenders and promiſes of free Grace.</hi> In the time of thy life, at the hour of thy death, and then when thou ſhalt be brought to thy tryal after death, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all things, <hi>and plead none but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61766:34"/>Chriſt.</hi> Cry <hi>pardon</hi> (Lord) <hi>juſtification</hi> (Lord) <hi>peace</hi> (Lord) <hi>life, glory, all for thy Chriſts ſake</hi> and upon the account of thy free grace.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Now wellcome Chriſt N.</hi> &amp; by <hi>W: if at death thou wilt be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed by Chriſt.</hi> Entertain Chriſt in the world, if thou wilt be entertained by Chriſt when thou goeſt out of the world. Many ſay unto Chriſt, <hi>depart now,</hi> as thoſe <hi>Job</hi> 21.13. To whom Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt will ſay, <hi>Depart then.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Chriſt in every approach and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to thy ſoul, to the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſay, <hi>Oh welcome Jeſus!</hi> Let the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers in preaching of Chriſt, be <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful even in their feet to thee:</hi> Let the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vidences, and occurrences of the grand changes in the world, by which Chriſt cometh to make way for, and to ſet up his own kingdom; let theſe be dear and welcome to thee. Fret not againſt, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur not under any diſpenſation in which Chriſt comes neer to thee or others. Welcom <hi>Chriſt in a ſickneſs though ſharp; in a ſermon though plain; in providence though terrible.</hi> In al things, in ev'ry thing wherein Chriſt is; O bid him <hi>welcome
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61766:34"/>now,</hi> ſo will he bid you we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ome when you come to <hi>dye.</hi> If you ask where hee'l bid you welcome? Take it in a word, Hee'l bid you welcom <hi>to his fathers houſe</hi> and hee'l carry you into a <hi>Manſion</hi> which he hath <hi>prepared</hi> for you in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers preſence.</p>
               <p>Thus are we come about our <hi>compaſs.</hi> We have run from <hi>North</hi> to <hi>North</hi> in a round. From <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>holineſs,</hi> from <hi>holineſſe</hi> to <hi>death;</hi> and by <hi>death</hi> we are in our Chriſtian circle come about to <hi>God</hi> again. And thus we have our princi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al Points in our Sea or Saint-Compaſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">The points on which the Chriſtian compaſs muſt turn, and the box in which it muſt be kept.</head>
               <p>I Had thoughts to have paſſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to my laſt head of ſpiritual Navigation. But I muſt add a word or two more. The occaſion is this, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my Sea-Compaſſe is lifted up upon
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61766:35"/>a <hi>point</hi> or pin which it turns and runs round upon; and there is a <hi>box</hi> in which it's kept and ſtands. Hereupon I ſhall add two words anſwerable to theſe two things.</p>
               <p n="2">Firſt for the <hi>point</hi> upon which our <hi>Compaſs</hi> muſt ſtand and <hi>turn,</hi> I cannot think of any other but <hi>CONSCIENCE A tender, quick, enlightned, and inlive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned conſcience is the only point upon which we muſt erect the practical rules of our Christian Compaſs.</hi> Minde that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Herein imitate that great Pilot <hi>Paul; Lab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> alwayes to have a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence void of offence towards God and man.</hi> That with him you may ſay, <hi>We truſt we have a good conſcience,</hi> Heb. 13.8. Indeed without this, there is no truſt to thoſe rules. <hi>What are the beſt rules, if men make no conſcience of them? A pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted compaſs upon the leaf of the book</hi> is of no uſe, to ſtere by. It muſt be an <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected compaſs ſet on a needle,</hi> which ſtirs and moves, by which our ſhip at Sea is to be guided and <hi>cunned.</hi> And <hi>written rules,</hi> though never ſo full or few are of no profit, if they be not laid upon the <hi>conſcience,</hi> and that conſcience quick
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61766:35"/>and tender. Remember therefore this as an <hi>additional,</hi> yet <hi>fundamental</hi> point, That <hi>if ever you will be the better for the former compaſſe, you must make conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the ſame.</hi> Eye it therefore, and out of <hi>conſcience unto God</hi> endeavor to ſteer according to it. In every point of thy <hi>compaſs,</hi> eye God as the main, and out of <hi>conſcience</hi> unto him, carry thy ſelfe in all things as neer as poſſible according to this <hi>compaſſe.</hi> Then may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou rejoyce, and expect that God upon thy endeavors ſhould ſpeak unto thee, Well done, ſteer away, or <hi>steer thus.</hi> And certainly it's no ſmal rejoyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thoſe things to have <hi>the teſtimony of our conſcience, that in all ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, by the grace of God we have had our converſation according to thoſe rules and that compaſſe,</hi> That may be, and thus are agreeable to his own word.</p>
               <p n="2">Secondly, For the <hi>box</hi> in which this <hi>comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe</hi> muſt be kept. I ſhall onely name our MEMORY. O treaſure ye theſe rules there; and ſtrive to be as ready and expert in this compaſſe, as the Mariner is in his Sea-Compaſſe I have
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61766:36"/>on purpoſe made this <hi>little, that our memory might hold it.</hi> Had I been as large as I might, I ſhould have made my compaſſe too large; and I fear the bigg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and beſt memories could not have contained it. But tis <hi>ſhort,</hi> that the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt memory might retain it. Wherefore do as our Seaboyes do at firſt, Con over this Compaſſe again and again. Get it into the <hi>head,</hi> nay into the <hi>heart;</hi> that when thou art any where (though in the dark, or deep) and canſt not have the help of larger diſcourſes, theſe things may be in thy memory to help thee <hi>rightly and ſafely</hi> to <hi>ſteer</hi> and carry thy ſelfe upon all occaſions. I will not ſay if thou remembreſt theſe things, thou needeſt no more. But this I do humbly aſſure thee of, <hi>If thou remember theſe things and doeſt them, thou ſhalt not miſcarry,</hi> but ſafely arrive at the Port of eternal felicity, where thou ſhalt have cauſe to bleſſe God for the little help of this <hi>ſhort Compaſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:61766:36"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <head type="sub">The third head of Divine Navigation opened, and ſpoke unto, <hi>viz.</hi> Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Meditation.</head>
               <p>I Called Divinity the Art of ſoul ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual-Navigation, and branched it out (<hi>Chap.</hi> 2.) into three heads, <hi>viz. Speculative, Practical,</hi> and <hi>Affectionate. I</hi> have diſpatched the two firſt, and ſhal now treat upon the laſt. <hi>Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate divinity doth principally lie in the ſecret motions or movings of the ſoul to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God in the Affections.</hi> Theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are raiſed and warmed, and eſpecially appear active in <hi>meditation.</hi> As affections are the motions of the ſoul (therfore by ſome ancient Philoſophers calld the <hi>feet of the ſoul</hi>) ſo mediation is the motion of the affections. The things therefore which <hi>I</hi> ſhal hint at, about the affections, I will put into ſome practicall rules of Meditation. <hi>Meditation</hi> being as it were a <hi>Lymbeck,</hi> or Still in which the affections heat and melt, and as it were drop ſweet ſpirituall waters. In this laſt part <hi>I</hi> ſhall therefore hint at ſome
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61766:37"/>
                  <hi>affectionate mediations</hi> which our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Seaman is to be acquainted with. Now my meditations ſhall be of two ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome meditations of a more ſingle <hi>ſimple nature;</hi> and others of a <hi>mixed,</hi> ſuch as wee call <hi>miſcellaneous.</hi> Fixed and <hi>ſimple meditations,</hi> are ſuch as may ariſe from ſome <hi>particular ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al texts of Scripture</hi> which concern Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; of this ſort <hi>I</hi> ſhall onely inſtance in two.</p>
               <p>Firſt that of <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 77.19. <hi>Thy way is in the Sea, and thy paths in the mighty waters.</hi> This Scripture in deed is uſed in a <hi>Spirituall ſenſe,</hi> with reference <hi>to the ſecret unknown wayes of God, in his act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the world, and in his dealings with his Saints.</hi> But yet it relates unto, and is ſpoke of God in alluſion to the <hi>literall Sea and waters,</hi> where God maketh his way; <hi>for he walketh, and is in the deeps, as on the dry.</hi> Hence meditate thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Why ſhould I fear dangers more, or ſin leſſe at Sea, then on the land!</hi> The Lord is here even in theſe mighty waters: Amidſt all thoſe rowling waves he walks and rules. Then though <hi>I</hi> ſteer in the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61766:37"/>mighty ocean, yet <hi>J'le fear no evil, for God is with me:</hi> And yet <hi>J'le fear to ſin,</hi> for God is here, as well as at land. Though I am not on ſhore neer Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, or puniſhing place; yet here, at Sea is the great God, who is chief Judge of all the world; therefore even here I'le ſtand in aw and ſin not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>See (oh my ſoul) is not here a place for worſhip as well as on land?</hi> Is not God here on the waters? and ought he not here to have his worſhip? This <hi>great ocean</hi> is no other then his <hi>open temple.</hi> Even here he walks; thoſe Seas and <hi>windes do ſerve him at his pleaſure.</hi> O my ſoul! <hi>worſhip thy God even here:</hi> Say not, ſhal <hi>I</hi> live on land, to go up to the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?</hi> Loe the Lord is nigh thee, even before thee. Worſhip thy God in the mighty waters; kneel before his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool, and adore his preſence even in the ſeas.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>What though thou be alone on theſe deeps</hi> (O my ſoul) <hi>as to relations, ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</hi> Though wife, children, friends &amp;c. be on <hi>ſhore;</hi> and thou (as to them) upon <hi>Sea</hi> alone, <hi>yet art not thou alone</hi> (altogether O my ſoul) <hi>for the Father is with thee.</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:61766:38"/>He walketh in the <hi>deep,</hi> while thou wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt on thy <hi>Deck.</hi> His path is in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and thou haſt alwayes his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Rejoyce (O my ſoul) thy God is at Sea, though all thy friends be at land.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Oh that mine eyes were enlightened to obſerve the inviſible paths which God makes in theſe waters.</hi> God is here, and <hi>I am not aware of it!</hi> The way of a <hi>ſhip in the Sea is not ſeen;</hi> how much leſs are the <hi>print of his feet, who is paſt finding out?</hi> Come, <hi>Oh thou Spirit of Annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting!</hi> And as God moves upon the face of the mighty waters, move thou on my ſoul, that I may ſee and apprehend the Divinity which ſwims in the deep.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>meditate on this Scripture, till thy ſoul melt in thoughts of God.</hi> And if at any time thy <hi>ſoul thinks of God, and is troubled,</hi> (as was <hi>Aſaphs,</hi> when hee ſpake or penn'd the words of this Pſalm, as appears in the beginning, <hi>ver.</hi> 2.) then in that very trouble remember, Gods way is in the waters: even in the midſt of thoſe <hi>waters of affliction</hi> (which came into thy very ſoul) the Lord is; and in them he is walking with thee. In
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61766:38"/>that <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>ſorrow and deſertion,</hi> wherein thou art as an afflicted Soul (ſhip-like) <hi>toſſed with tempeſt</hi> (as it is <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.11.) <hi>and xot comforted:</hi> Minde this, that the Lords <hi>path is in the Sea, and his footſteps are not known.</hi> Therefore hee may be, and is with thee, though thou ſee him not; and he may be preparing choyce <hi>calm refreſhings</hi> for thee though thou perceive it not. Indeed that is the ſcope of this Scripture.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.23, 24, 25, to the 31. <hi>They that go down to the Sea in ſhips, that do buſineſs in great waters.</hi> 24. <hi>Theſe ſee the works of the Lord, and his wonders in the deep.</hi> 25. <hi>For he commandeth, and raiſeth the ſtormy winde, which lifteth up the waves thereof.</hi> 26. <hi>They mount up to the heavens, they go down again to the depths; their ſoul is melted becauſe of trouble.</hi> 27. <hi>They reel to and fro, and ſtagger like a drunken man, and are at their wits end.</hi> 28. <hi>Then they cry unto the Lord in their troubles, and he bringeth them out of their distreſs.</hi> 29. <hi>He maketh the ſtorm a calme, ſo that the waves thereof are ſtill.</hi> 30. <hi>Then are they glad becauſe they are quiet: ſo he bringeth
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61766:39"/>them to their deſired Haven.</hi> 31. <hi>O that men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs, and for his wonderfull works to the children of men!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On this Scripture meditate much; and to help thy Meditations, note in it theſe particulars.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Obſerve of whom it ſpeaks,</hi> viz. of Seamen; ſo all along the Verſes, <hi>They that go down to the Sea, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>To what end, viz.</hi> That they ſhould conſider their affairs, obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and experiences, in order to the raiſing of their hearts to ſee and praiſe God for his goodneſs, ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 3.</item>
               </list>
               <p>But more expreſs, to help exact medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, remember that here is ſet forth;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The man at Sea upon civill accounts,</hi> verſe 23.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The spiritual work or duty of him in that his buſineſſe;</hi> and this is ſet forth in many branches.
<list>
                        <item>1 <hi>He is to eye</hi> God <hi>in his works and wonders,</hi> v: 24.</item>
                        <item>2. <hi>He is to eye</hi> God <hi>in every ſtorm and tempeſt.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>1 <hi>As the author of it,</hi> v. 25:</item>
                              <item>2 <hi>As the helper in it,</hi> v: 29: Therefore,</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:61766:39"/>
                        <item>3 <hi>He is to conſider his danger in every ſtorm,</hi> how neer to death, and how full of dread or fear, v. 26, 27.</item>
                        <item>4 <hi>He is to know his duty in that danger,</hi> v. 28.</item>
                        <item>5 <hi>He is to conſider his joy at the end of danger,</hi> as ver. 30.</item>
                        <item>6. <hi>He is to remember to praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs,</hi> upon the whole, verſe 31. Now upon theſe heads meditate thus.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>O my ſoul! the way in which thou art is ſafe;</hi> for 'tis lawful to traffick by Sea as by Land. There is no wickedneſs in thy way, unleſs thou thy ſelf do make it. The Lord as well allowes, approves, and proſpers thoſe whoſe buſineſs is to do in the <hi>great waters,</hi> as whoſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings are on the <hi>ſhore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>But what of</hi> God <hi>do I ſee and eye in my way?</hi> I am to walk with God <hi>Enoch</hi>-like, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24. and as a childe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Gen.</hi> 17.1. So <hi>Noah</hi> did who was the firſt that ever ſwam in ſhip. Hee walked with God righteouſly on the dry, and God ſecured him in a ſhip of his own invention in the mighty wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. I am not to be as the ſhip at ſea,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61766:40"/>a ſenſleſs inſtrument, not kowing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſail, or what I carry, or where <hi>I</hi> am; Neither am <hi>I</hi> only to eye Winde and Tide, but I am to ſee God, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template him in all. Theſe <hi>waters are his work.</hi> He made them, <hi>and gathered them thus together,</hi> Gen. 1.10. He holds theſe windes that blow <hi>in the hollow of his fiſt,</hi> Prov. 30.4. he brings theſe windes out of <hi>his treaſure,</hi> Jer. 10.13. And <hi>he rides upon the wings thereof,</hi> Pſal. 60.4. Mount (my ſoul) above theſe <hi>windes</hi> and <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and ſee thy God in them; for they are his works. And ſurely wonderfull is God in working! vvhat <hi>wiſdome in ordering!</hi> vvhat <hi>power in bounding and ruling theſe unruly things,</hi> Job 38.8, 9, 10, 11. ſee the place, and meditate thereon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Doth a tempeſt ariſe? <hi>Sit down</hi> (O my ſoul) <hi>and ſee that it comes from God.</hi> He made the tempeſt to finde out a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Jonah.</hi> He permits this, <hi>to try my ſaith; to ſtir up my prayer; to demonſtrate his own power.</hi> As afflictions ariſes not out of the duſt; ſo neither do Tempeſts come by chance. <hi>A God is in all;</hi> he raiſeth, and he can ſtill vvhen he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:61766:40"/>the boyſterous <hi>windes</hi> and <hi>waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Yet <hi>conſider what is thy danger.</hi> How neer to death? What a <hi>ſtep,</hi> what an <hi>inch</hi> between thee and the grave? Bee not as the fool over-hardy; nor as the hardened prophane Athieſt, that ſcoffs at windes, and feareth no <hi>weathers.</hi> Tremble (O my ſoul) the next <hi>guſt</hi> may overſet thee; the next wave may ſwallow thee up. O be not unaffected with, nor inconſiderate of thy danger!</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Vp then and call upon thy</hi> God, Jon. 1.6. <hi>That is thy duty in thy danger:</hi> Slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not, but poure out prayers to him that made and can ſtill the Tempeſt at his pleaſure; hold thy <hi>ſails</hi> with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>Sighs;</hi> hand thy <hi>cords</hi> and <hi>tack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> with a <hi>Heart ſecretly praying.</hi> Let thy beſt <hi>anchor</hi> be <hi>within the vail;</hi> pray in faith, cry in hope. The Almighty can with a word make a <hi>calm, Pſa.</hi> 65.7. Chriſt can ſay, <hi>Be ſtill,</hi> and <hi>Windes</hi> and <hi>Sea</hi> muſt and will obey him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.27. Have thy <hi>hand at the helm,</hi> and thy <hi>eye at heaven;</hi> God it may be raiſed the ſtorm to awake thee from thy ſoul-ſleep. Riſe up therefore and call upon God; hee'l bring you out of your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:61766:41"/>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Reflect (O man) then what was thy joy when the winde began to ſlack and the storm to ceaſe.</hi> It's good to eye what comforts God gave in at ſuch a time. Forget neither thy ſoul-meltings in a ſtorm, nor thy heart-cheering upon a calm. O how did God as it were build up thy broken heart? was not thy ſoul almoſt ſhattered as thy ſails? and were not all thy comforts broke as thy cords? But what reviving after death; and what a reſurrection as from the grave hadſt thou in ſuch a place at ſuch a time? &amp;c. was not thy ſoul refreſhed as with wine? and thy ſpirit recovered as with a cordial, when after that, or the other Tempeſt, <hi>God</hi> gave a calm?</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Then praiſe thy Lord [O my ſoule] and forget not ALL, nar not ANY of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits.</hi> Record &amp; recal to mind the great goodneſs of thy <hi>God,</hi> and praiſe thou his miraculous mercy. Set forth to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thy experiences, and let the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men know by thee, what are the wonderful works of <hi>Jehovah.</hi> Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the thought of being (as too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are) altogether forgetful of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances. Be not as thoſe <hi>whoſe ſinning
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61766:41"/>at land, evidences they forget every ſtorm and danger, every mercy and deliverance at Sea.</hi> But, Oh do thou (my ſoul) <hi>praiſe the Lord for his wonderfull works to thee (the pooreſt of the children of men.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Inlarge theſe and the like Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon this Scripture; and by them try the like way of meditaring upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <head type="sub">Mixed maritine, or Sea-meditations to ſtir up ſpiritual affections.</head>
               <p>I Have hinted an example of medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon Scripture, I will now offer ſome <hi>mixed</hi> Meditations relating to Sea-affairs, ſuch as may ſerve to excite and direct in this third and laſt part of Divinity, <hi>viz.</hi> affectionate.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>What a little thing is between me and death.</hi> It's but this board of which the ſhip is made, if that break I am gone; my burial place is alwayes by me; I ſhal need no <hi>Sexton</hi> to dig my grave; my dead body will make its way
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:61766:42"/>to the bottom of the waters, and there ſhall be my grave till the great day.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>With what care doth the Pilot eye the Compaſs to direct? How exactly doth he obſerve and conſider all his land marks?</hi> And how careful is the <hi>ſteerſman</hi> at the <hi>helm,</hi> to hearken to, and to follow his direction! <hi>O what negligent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are we in our spiritual Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion!</hi> How ſhort do we come of this care and circumſpection? As if the ſhipwrack of our ſouls were a leſſer matter then the ſhipwrack of this veſſel.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>How ſharp do all the ſhips crew look out to eſpy land, to diſcover ſhoar and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour whereto they ſail?</hi> And what wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come newes is it to hear that he at the <hi>topmaſt head</hi> hath deſcryed or diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Land, though it be afar off! Ah (my ſoul!) <hi>why art thou ſo lazie to look out?</hi> So backward to caſt thine eyes, to uſe thy <hi>Proſpective</hi> to diſcover <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuels</hi> Land, which is afar off? What! is not the <hi>Haven of Heaven</hi> worthy thy obſervation? Is it not joy to hear (by thy watchman) that thou art neer the fair haven of the holy Land? Look out, look up (O ſoul) and rejoyce to ſee
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61766:42"/>how neer thou art to thy bleſſed port.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>What care is there of this cable to preſerve and ſtrengthen it, both that it may hold faſt to the Anchor, and that it may not break any where, but hold faſt the ſhip to it?</hi> Surely I have in my veſſell both my Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles I have in my veſſell both my Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Anchor too, (<hi>The great promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of grace, and the good hope which is through that grace,</hi> as it is 2 Theſſ. 2.16) and this <hi>Anchor</hi> is caſt <hi>within the vail,</hi> Heb. 6.19. where it hath ſure ground, from whence it will not ſlip. Why do I not carefully and diligently attend it? Why do I not ſtudy to ſecure theſe Cables and this Anchor, that in every ſtorm and tempeſt they may ſecure me?</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>With what deſires do all the Seamen tarry and pray for a good winde?</hi> How troubled are they at a croſs winde? and how much perplexed at a <hi>calm?</hi> What means all this, but a deſire to ſpeed the voyage, and to arrive the intended and deſired Port, which a calme and no winde doth as well hinder as a ſtorm and croſs winde. Call thou (O my ſoule) upon the <hi>Spirit</hi> (who is the <hi>breath of God,</hi> and the <hi>winde of the ſoul-ſhip</hi>) call upon him to ariſe &amp; blow.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61766:43"/>Be grieved when thou art <hi>becalmed,</hi> ſo as that thou muſt float and fluctuate upon the waters of this world for want of the winde and gales of the Spirit. Mourn likewiſe when thou art hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo as that thou canſt not ſpeed, and haſte in thy Heavenly Voyage, by reaſon of croſs breathings and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite windes of thy corruptions. Be ſure diligently to obſerve everie gale; ſpread all thy <hi>ſailes;</hi> neglect no opportunity; <hi>take the winde of the Spirit when it blows,</hi> and rejoyce, that in the help of it t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou haſteſt to thy deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red port.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>What labour and paines doe all take in a ſtorme?</hi> How do theſe tend the ſails, and thoſe the pump? How do theſe ſtand by this, and the others by the other rope? And how do all ſecretly [at leaſt] cry out and ſay, <hi>Lord ſave us, that we periſh not!</hi> Why then doeſt thou (O my ſoule) <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi>-like lye and ſleep ſecurely in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a tempeſt which doth befall thee? Is the ſinking of thy ſoul leſs then the periſhing of a ſhip? or art reſolved de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately to go <hi>a-drift,</hi> to ſee if God
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61766:43"/>will ſave thee at a <hi>venture?</hi> O take heed of this, <hi>Awake and call upon thy God; up and take hold of the means.</hi> Set every fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty a work: <hi>This is the hour and power of darkneſs,</hi> as Chriſt ſaid, [truly we may ſpeak it of our preſent times.] If ever there were a tempeſtuous time now it is. Soul! art inſenſible? Doſt not thou ſee before thee many an <hi>Alexandrean,</hi> and <hi>Hymean</hi> ſhipwrack, as it is, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19. Hark! The windes blow, the floods ariſe, thy ſails and rigging are rent and torn; many a ſtately ſhip is ſunk by thee; and thy leaks are more then the <hi>pump</hi> of thy <hi>repentance</hi> can clear; yet hope in God, and be labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; though ſalvation be of grace, yet good ſecurity is not without works and diligence.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>How doth each Mariner and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man eye, and care for the whole crew as well as himſelf?</hi> How doth he mainly intend the ſafety of the <hi>whole veſſell,</hi> while yet he ſingly cares for his own <hi>Cabbin?</hi> What a ſafe and ſweet har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is there between the care of the <hi>whole</hi> and each <hi>particular part?</hi> And how well doth <hi>ſelfe</hi> and the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:61766:44"/>conſiſt together? <hi>Fool that I am, why do I not thus in the ſhip of the Church,</hi> ſeek as well the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as of my ſelfe? <hi>Minde ſo my owne, as not to neglect others;</hi> and minde ſo others, as yet particularly to minde my ſelfe. How many (like him in the Goſpel) ask concerning the number or multitude of ſuch as ſhall be ſaved; and yet in the interim, neglect to ſtir themſelves to ſecure their own ſalvation, by ſtriving to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at the ſtrait gate? And how many ſo ſingly eye themſelves, and enquire what <hi>they ſhall do to be ſaved;</hi> that they ſeem altogether to neglect, and not to care for others? <hi>Steer</hi> (Oh my ſoul!) <hi>a ſtrait courſe between theſe rocks;</hi> regard thy <hi>ſelf,</hi> and yet minde thy <hi>fellow-paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers.</hi> Let not <hi>ſelf-privacy</hi> wrong the <hi>publike,</hi> nor a <hi>Pragmatick publickneſs</hi> cheat ſelf.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>How oft hath a calm evening deceived the Seaman, who when he thought he might go to his cabbin and ſleep ſecurely, hath bin raiſed up in half a watch by ſome unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and boyſterous ſtorm?</hi> And on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her hand, <hi>How hath ſome ſtormy day
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61766:44"/>(which made the Seamen fear a tempestu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſad night)</hi> how oft hath ſuch a day ended <hi>in a calm at night?</hi> So that when he thought to watch with fear, he could go and lie down to ſleep in peace. Surely thus it hath bin more then once with thee [O my ſoul] in the voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age over the Sea of this world. Many a ſtorm haſt thou unexpectedly met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, when viſible appearances promiſed nothing but peace &amp; joy; ſo that when-as thou haſt ſaid, <hi>I wil lie me down in peace &amp;c. and my mountain is ſo ſure I ſhal not be moved;</hi> how upon a ſudden hath <hi>God hid his face, and the tempter aroſe</hi> in a tempeſt and thou wert ſuddenly <hi>troubled?</hi> ſo that where thou wert ready to ſay, I am in peace, &amp; may reſt <hi>ſweetly,</hi> Trouble came and thou wert <hi>afflicted, and toſſed as with a tempeſt, and not comforted.</hi> But canſt not thou call to minde on the contrary to thy <hi>Redeemers praiſe,</hi> that ſomtime <hi>thou haſt expected trouble, and yet haſt met with peace?</hi> And when thou haſt ſaid [<hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah-</hi>like] <hi>I ſhal go in bitterneſs ſoftly all my dayes;</hi> then hath not the Lord ere thou didſt expect it, ſpeak <hi>peace in the blood of the Croſs,</hi> &amp; by the word of the <hi>Promiſe?</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:61766:45"/>ſo that about <hi>the evening time</hi> [when thodidſt fear a night of darkneſs and tempeſt] <hi>it was light,</hi> and thou couldſt reſt and lie down with joy in the bed of grace, in the boſome of Jeſus. Recall (O ſoul) thy ſpiritual experiences to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance by theſe ſea-obſervations.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>How beautiful is the ſhip, when un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſail, going before a fair winde, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king fine weather?</hi> With what eaſe and cheerfulneſs do all the ſailors tend their buſineſs? And how ſweet and pleaſant is ſuch a paſſage, when neither windes nor waves do in the leaſt interrupt or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the ſhip in its courſe? Hath it not been thus ſometimes with thee (O my ſoul) <hi>hast not thou ſometimes ſailed with a full and fair gale?</hi> Have not the winds above thee, and the waters under thee, ſweetly ſerved thee in thy voyage? Haſt not ſpeeded well, and ſailed farr upon ſome <hi>Watches?</hi> Verily it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes thee to call to minde ſuch former dayes, and to render praiſe <hi>even for what is paſt:</hi> And by or from the thought of ſome former Soul-calm, and ſweet experiences (which then thou haſt enjoyed) to learne
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:61766:45"/>to live, and <hi>hope</hi> in any tempeſt and ſtorm that hereafter thou mayeſt meet withall.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>How uſeful and ſerviceable is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Rope, yea the leaſt (about the ſhip) in its proper place?</hi> And how well skilled are the Sea-men in them? How do they know them all by name? and with what dexterity and ſtrength do they hand, and hale, and hold any of them as occaſion is? <hi>Surely</hi> (O my ſoul!) <hi>all thy ſpiritual tackling is uſeful and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. Every word of God is good.</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>precept, promiſe, threatning, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp;c. all,</hi> and <hi>each</hi> of theſe are occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally to be remembred &amp; <hi>improved:</hi> yea every <hi>work</hi> and <hi>providence,</hi> every <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>affliction</hi> ſhould be known (as it were) by Name: And wert thou but divinely dextrous, and ſpiritually skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, thou mighteſt make ſpecial uſe of all in thy ſpiritual Navigation.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>The ſhip hath not onely Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize and treaſure in its hold, but it carryes force and ſtrength upon its Decks.</hi> Here are inſtruments of war; guns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſecure from enemies and pyrates, as well as Commodities to traffick with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61766:46"/>all. And <hi>ſurely</hi> (O my ſoul) <hi>it becomes thee to minde the weapons of thy warfare,</hi> that whole Armor of God, which out of the Magazine of the Scriptures thou art to be furniſhed withall. Go into, and take a ſight of the Armory as 'tis opened <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>There are Enemyes and Pyrates upon the ſoul-Sea:</hi> Men (yea and devils) of wrath and war, that way-lay thee. Expect an on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, and provide. <hi>None ever did paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Sea of the world, but met with Pyrates.</hi> Thou muſt reſiſt and fight <hi>(yea, and that unto blood)</hi> to ſecure thy ſelf from being taken or ſunk. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this, and look about thee (O my ſoul) thou carryeſt <hi>petty Pyrates within thee,</hi> that will never fight for thee, (fleſh will not fight againſt the world and Satan) nay, <hi>which war againſt thy ſoul.</hi> Look to it therefore to <hi>watch againſt thoſe within,</hi> that thou mayeſt the better maintain thy fight with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Still by our Helm ſtands the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, that the ſteerſman may alwayes eye it.</hi> As ſoon as his hand is on the <hi>Helm,</hi> his eye is on the <hi>Compaſſe;</hi> and with
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:61766:46"/>what exactneſs &amp; ſtrength doth he hold the Helm, to ſteer to a point by that! Thus it <hi>becomes thee</hi> (O my poor ſoul) <hi>to eye thy Compaſſe in all thy stirring and ſteering up and down the world.</hi> It's not enough to hand and hold the <hi>Helm,</hi> to put forth ſtrength to <hi>ſtir and do,</hi> (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this is very good againſt idleneſs) but thou muſt <hi>eye the rule,</hi> that while thou ſtirreſt it may be <hi>within</hi> (as we ſay) are according to <hi>Compaſſe. Many who are not idle, are yet evil employed;</hi> who though they <hi>ſtir,</hi> yet it's not according to <hi>compaſſe;</hi> and it is a thouſand to one if they run not aground upon ſome Rock ot Sand. But <hi>let the word</hi> be in thy hand, in thy heart; <hi>keep it, that it may guide thee.</hi> Remember &amp; retain it. (O my ſoul) as a certain truth, That they make ſhipwrack of their ſoul who ey not, and ſteer not according to Compaſs, how active and zealous ſoever they be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. Actions that are irregular and without Compaſs, are as bad as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect idleneſs, if not often worſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:61766:47"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <head type="sub">Here are ſome occaſional Meditations to ſtir up, and to direct in this work.</head>
               <p>I Have now almoſt done, only to theſe <hi>Maritine Meditations,</hi> which I call <hi>mixed,</hi> as being of ſundry ſorts; I ſhall add twelve more <hi>occaſional ones</hi> drawn from ſome particular occaſions; and then I'le conclude.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>On the Boatſwains Whiſtle.</head>
                  <p>What a <hi>ſhril ſound</hi> doth this <hi>whiſtle make?</hi> How is it heard both <hi>fore and ought,</hi> above and beneath Deck? And how ready is every one at the ſound thereof? Surely there <hi>is no vertue in this Whiſtle,</hi> onely the <hi>Sea-men know the ſound,</hi> and uſe thereof, and 'tis there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that they are ſo ready at its call to come. Both <hi>John and Jeſus piped</hi> (O my ſoul) <hi>but the refractory Jews ſtirred not;</hi> ſurely they knew not what that ſound meant. But <hi>ſhew thy life and ſkill,</hi> (O my ſoul) <hi>and upon any ſound of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:61766:47"/>words whiſtle, ſtir:</hi> Upon every blaſt of ſacred breath which ſounds that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſilver pipe, up, and ſee what it means O let the ſound thereof be ſhrill and powerful on thy heart!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>On a piece of Plank floating on the Sea.</head>
                  <p>Yonder ſwims the ſad <hi>ſigne</hi> of the <hi>wracke</hi> of ſome: I conclude the <hi>ſinking</hi> of the paſſenger, from the <hi>ſwimming</hi> of the Plank. Bleſſed Lord, <hi>Why,</hi> (ſuffer me to ask it) <hi>why didſt not ſave ſome one upon that piece of Timber?</hi> might not that board, or <hi>broken piece</hi> have been <hi>(as in Pauls caſe)</hi> a little Ark to ſave ſome from drowning by carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to ſhore? But <hi>pardon my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in this queſtion.</hi> Yet it may be there wanted a <hi>Paul</hi> in the veſſel, to whom thou mighteſt <hi>have given all that did ſail therein.</hi> But why ſhould I ſo i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine, and uncharitably ſink them lower who are gone down into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the great deep. <hi>Turnin</hi> (O my ſoul) <hi>upon thy ſelf, reflect and ſee what might have befallen thee:</hi> That Plank
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:61766:48"/>might have been thy <hi>floating Tomb, or Monument,</hi> that ſome other paſſenger might have read on it thy departure by drowning. <hi>Be not high-minded then, but fear.</hi> Admire mercy in preſerving thee. The ſame hand that broke that Veſſel in pieces, (whereof that Plank or piece of Timber was) can ſplit thee at his pleaſure. And the next paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers may ſee the broken pieces of the ſhip in which thou wert, and read a better Lecture on them then thou doſt on this; making better uſe both of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and improvement by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>On a Sea-man which fell aſleep in the ſhrouds, and fell down in the Sea while the Sermon was preaching, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>What another <hi>Eutychus</hi> is here! yet there's a difference. <hi>Eutychus</hi> in the <hi>Acts</hi> (chap. 20.) was aſleep in the <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and he ſunk down from the third loft,</hi> ſaith the holy Hiſtorian: but this yong man was <hi>aſleep in the ſhrowds</hi> of a ſhip, and ſunk down into the Sea. <hi>Eutychus</hi> was dead with the fall, this young man
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:61766:48"/>but almoſt drowned. <hi>Eutychus</hi> had a fairer excuſe for his drowſineſs <hi>(for it was in the night)</hi> then this young man, who fell aſleep at the <hi>noon</hi> of the day: Yet [O my ſoul] canſt not ſay this, to excuſe this young man, <hi>He had not ſo holy, ſo rowzing a Preacher as</hi> Eutychus <hi>had.</hi> Alas! how far art thou (O my ſoul) beneath <hi>Paul!</hi> Well, let the yong man learn to be leſs drowzy; and be thou more awaking &amp; ſtirring in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. Yet tell others (O my ſoul) 'tis <hi>dangerous ſleeping in Sermon-time.</hi> Bid them to look <hi>about them,</hi> to attend to the word of life, <hi>leſt they ſleep the ſleep of death,</hi> and ſink down from a corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to a ſpiritual ſleep, never to awake till they are rowzed up to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for that Sermon, at which they they ſlept and dyed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>On a great diſtraction in the Navy, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly and ſafely ended on a Sabbath day.</head>
                  <p>'Twas but this morning we received orders to prepare and be in readineſs to fight. <hi>It was indeed in an evil time, becauſe it was upon a good day.</hi> A <hi>fight</hi> is
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:61766:49"/>as well a miſery on the Sabbath day, as a <hi>fight,</hi> and both are equally to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt. Yet neceſſity hath a no Law. <hi>And Joſhua's ſeven dayes compaſſing about Jericho,</hi> will be a preſident for us to lye about thoſe Ships in a war-like poſture, ſeeing we are put upon it. But (O my ſoul) what cannot God do? <hi>He that made</hi> Jericho <hi>fall at the ſound of Rams horns, hath made ſhips give up and yeeld at the ſound of fellow-Sea-men, exhorting to yeeld to ſubjection.</hi> We ſhall not need I ſee ſometimes to uſe our guns; words can conquer when God will. Now <hi>I know indeed that the Lord can make wars to ceaſe;</hi> or as the word is, Pſal. 46 9. <hi>Turns war into a Sabbath, when a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath might have turned into a War.</hi> Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I'le praiſe the Lord, <hi>and ſing; it's the Lord that ſtilleth the noyſe of the Seas, the voice of their waves, and the tumult of the people,</hi> Pſal. 65.7 He diſappoints the devices of crafty <hi>Captains,</hi> and makes the <hi>common Mariners</hi> to yeeld up them, that blood may not be ſhed, nor peace broken. God makes even men at Sea, as well as waves, to be calm and ſtill.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:61766:49"/>
                  <head>On a man that standing to ſound with the line, fell over-board, and was loſt.</head>
                  <p>This man ſounded to <hi>ſecure the ſhip,</hi> yet he <hi>lost himſelf.</hi> He ſtood with the line and lead to ſound <hi>what depth of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> the Veſſel had, and he falls into the waters, and ſo himſelf ſunk to the <hi>bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom to feel the depth.</hi> Ah, O my ſoul! Is not this man an Embleme of thee, who ſoundeſt the <hi>depths of Satan</hi> to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure others? Art not thou in danger to looſe thy ſelf? <hi>Preachers look about you;</hi> fear, leſt while you ſound and diſcourſe of <hi>Satans deeps</hi> to warn others, fear (I ſay) leſt you loſe your ſelves. <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners look to it,</hi> while you ſtand by the line and lead ſounding. Conſider, that you may be <hi>neerer the bottom</hi> then you are aware; 'twill be ſad if you fall and ſink even while you ſound: but ſadder, if as your <hi>body,</hi> like the <hi>lead,</hi> goes down the <hi>bottom of the deep,</hi> your ſoul ſink as a <hi>ſtone</hi> into the depth of hell. You had need be well skilled in the <hi>art and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of spiritual ſwimming,</hi> that ſo your ſouls may be ſecure and ſafe by ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:61766:50"/>to the banks of heavens ſhore, when your bodies ſink to the bottom of the Seas.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>On the ſight of many great ſhot made from a Fort to ſome Veſſels, and none taking place.</head>
                  <p>Surely the <hi>gunner intended to hit and hurt,</hi> however he <hi>ſtill miſſed the mark:</hi> he traverſed and levelled to miſchief veſſel and men, but yet ſtill his bullet flew over &amp; beſides both. <hi>Seest thou not</hi> (O my ſoul) <hi>how it's God who guides the Bullet, while man fires the Gun?</hi> Divine providence can at pleaſure diſappoint the gunners intents. <hi>Bullets obey God, not men:</hi> and he that is under the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Almighty is (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) <hi>i.e. Shot-free.</hi> Why then ſhould they who are on the ſervice of God, and a good cauſe, fear men or guns? both whoſe <hi>breath</hi> is in their <hi>Noſtrils,</hi> and at <hi>Gods dispoſe;</hi> and who may ſhoot often, but hit or hurt never without divine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. Sail by, go on ſecurely (ye men of of war, who are upon divine deſigns) paſs by ſorts, by the ſides of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61766:50"/>ſhips. A thouſand ſhot ſhall flye a-<hi>head,</hi> and as many more a-<hi>ſtern;</hi> many fall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and beyond you, and none ſhall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to do you the leaſt hurt, while God is with you. All Bullets flye at Gods command, and not according to the gunners intent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>On the ſight of one corrected at the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock for an offence.</head>
                  <p>How do men obſerve and puniſh of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences in all places! This Veſſel is the Sea-mans <hi>habitation,</hi> and <hi>houſe of corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> and the ſame inſtrument which holds the <hi>anchor</hi> of hope, ſometimes holds the offender to be chaſtiſed. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed [O my ſoul] <hi>chaſtiſement is at the capſtock of the anchor of hope.</hi> It's a hope we are <hi>children and not baſtards, if we are chaſtiſed.</hi> Who then would preſume to ſin, when in all places there are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? and yet who would faint under any affliction, when as he is ſo near the <hi>hold</hi> of the anchor of hope? <hi>I'le fear thee my God</hi> (and Lord put thy fear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my heart, that I may ſay and hold) <hi>never preſuming to offend at Land or Sea;</hi>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:61766:51"/>for thou canſt puniſh me in all places at thy pleaſure; yet <hi>still I'le hope</hi> under <hi>every puniſhment.</hi> For verily, <hi>'tis good that a man accept of the puniſhment of his iniquity with patience and with hope.</hi> Next to be free from offending; the next mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to that, is to be chaſtiſed near and by hope.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>On the fall of a bed (that was laſhed to the ſhip ſide) in a blowing night.</head>
                  <p>I did lye <hi>down in peace,</hi> and thought to have ſlept ſo; but how is <hi>my bed faln under me?</hi> and how am I awakened with a fall, when I expected to lye ſoft and ſecure? But <hi>ſee</hi> (O my ſoul) <hi>what poor things beds are to reſt in.</hi> Surely no Bed in this world is faſtned ſure enough to ſecure ſleep and ſafety. Though the <hi>feathers are ſoft, the faſtening is not ſure.</hi> How can that Bed ſtand, that <hi>alway rowles upon, on the waves of a tempeſtuous world?</hi> The next blaſt (O ſecure ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py man) may ſhake thy bed, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſe or break thy cords, and then where is all thy ſecurity and expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of reſt? <hi>Make ſure (O my ſoul) of a
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:61766:51"/>better bed, and in a better cabine then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in this world.</hi> Caſt thy ſelf into thy <hi>Saviours boſome:</hi> That bed is ſoft and ſure; let the windes blow, and the floods ariſe, let the ſhip rowle, and thy cords ſhake; yet ſtill that <hi>bed</hi> ſhall abide and not be <hi>ſhaken.</hi> When thou goeſt to bed in thy <hi>Cabbin</hi> (O Sea man) thou art not ſure of reſt; but thou who reſteſt in Chriſt, thy reſt is ſure; and in him thou maiſt lye thee down in <hi>peace and ſleep, for he onely can make thee to dwell and rest in ſafety.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>On a boy at the topmaſt head looking out to deſcry land.</head>
                  <p>How <hi>nimbly</hi> did that boy run up the ſhrowds, and clime that Topmaſt? and how ſharply doth he looke out for land? yea, how doth the Maſter attend his report? <hi>I ſee now that hee who deſires to ſee the land afar off, muſt clime high.</hi> A lowe ſtation cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:61766:52"/>the remote banks of <hi>Emmanuels land.</hi> He that will ſpye the <hi>white clifts of heavens fair ſhoare,</hi> muſt mount the <hi>Topmaſt,</hi> and <hi>Habbakkuk</hi>-like ſet him upon his tower. And hearken (O ſoule) to the report of him on the Topmaſt. <hi>What chman what of the night,</hi> what of the day, what of land, <hi>what of the ſhore?</hi> Surely me-thinks I hear the report, the land is yet afar off; wee ſhall ſee it: but it may be ere we <hi>come to an anchor, our heart may meditate ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</hi> Yet rejoyce in this, that we are within ken of the <hi>good land,</hi> A few <hi>Watches more we muſt run</hi> (and indeed we muſt <hi>watch</hi> as we <hi>ſail</hi>) and then we ſhall ſee <hi>eye to eye,</hi> and diſcern the fair haven, fairly open for us to enter, and land where we long to be.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:61766:52"/>
                  <head>On an Anchor that lost its hold, and came home and left the ſhip adrift.</head>
                  <p>This <hi>Anchor</hi> ſure had not good <hi>ground;</hi> For if it had, it would have kept its hold, and not have left the ſhip thus to drive. <hi>I ſee the anchor of hope will not ſerve the turne, to hold the ſoul in a tempeſt, except the ground of that hope be good.</hi> There is a hope which hath but an evill ground, and in the day of diſtreſs it will fail, and force the ſoul to drive. O my ſoule, look to thy Hope; ſee where thou caſteſt it. <hi>Be ſure thy Anchor be within the vaile.</hi> Hope is not good, nor grounded, except on Chriſt and free-grace. Now <hi>the Lord Jeſus Christ himſelfe, and God even the Father, who hath loved mee, and hath given me everlaſting conſolation, and good hope through grace;</hi> even that ſame God <hi>comfort my heart,</hi> and <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſheth me in every good word and work;</hi> that though my hope be <hi>ſingly grounded</hi> on grace, yet it may bee <hi>accompanied
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:61766:53"/>with good words and works;</hi> that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not my ſelf, leſt my anchor come home, and I run afloat ful of fear, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hopes, or hold, in the day of <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt and tryals.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>On a ſhip that was left by the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners upon the Goodwin-ſands in a ſtorm, and fetcht off by ſome Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſent to relieve it by my Lord of <hi>VVarwick.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>What <hi>fearful</hi> and <hi>unfaithful Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> were theſe, that left the <hi>Veſſel</hi> to ſink, and ſhifted for themſelves, while their ſtay and pains might have ſecured themſelves and it well enough! Ah Lord, <hi>may the ſhip of the ſtate never meet with ſuch Mariners.</hi> But if that doth, ſtir up ſome noble <hi>Warwicks</hi> to ſend relief, to ſecure the ſhip which the perfidious Seamen cowardly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionably deſert. <hi>Truſt not in men</hi> (Oh my ſoul) <hi>who are unſtable as the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:61766:53"/>waters.</hi> Rely only upon the living God, who never forſakes his in a ſtorm or tempeſt. If they prove fearfull and falſe that ought to tend thy ſecurity, God can raiſe up others, if he pleaſes, to fetch thee off at any time from any rocks or ſands. Yea, if men fail, <hi>Sands</hi> ſhall be ſo good, as to keep thee from <hi>wracking,</hi> till Jehovah <hi>ſend help from above to ſave thee from the waters</hi> on which thou ſaileſt, that thou ſink not and periſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>On the parting of a ſhips company at the end of a voyage.</head>
                  <p>With what joy do theſe all part? and how glad are theſe men to leave each other, and yet without any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice or ill will? They love each other as companions, and yet are glad to part company; this is indeed a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>farewell of friends.</hi> Why ſhould it not be thus <hi>between thy ſoul and body</hi> (O my heart) <hi>at the end of thy voyage,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:61766:54"/>when death comes and calls upon thee to ſtrike ſail and part.</hi> Why art ſo loath to leave the carkaſe [thy companion] when thou art to go aſhore in thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon <hi>Emmannels</hi> land? Come, leap and skip O ſoul, part with the <hi>carkaſe</hi> with joy. Thy <hi>voyage is ended, thy months are out:</hi> Go take thy <hi>pay,</hi> receive thy <hi>wages;</hi> which yet is of <hi>grace,</hi> and not of <hi>works.</hi> Be as glad to go out of the body, and to leave it, as the Seaman is to leave his ſhip. Yet remember you ſhall return to your ſhip again: when <hi>Mortality ſhall have put on Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> your body ſhall be new rigged and trimmed up. And though at the end of time in the World to come, <hi>John</hi> tells us there ſhall be no Sea, yet the Pſalmiſt tells us there ſhall be a <hi>River of Pleaſures,</hi> on which thy ſoul and body ſhall ſail and ſwim in an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall calm of unexpreſſable bliſs in the preſence of God, in the company of Chriſt, Angels and Saints, for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Strike fail here, O my ſoul, and turmoyle thy ſelf on the Sea of this World no longer.</p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:61766:54"/>
                  <p>THeſe were ſome occaſional Meditations of my own in the yeer, 1642. when I was at ſea. And I make them thus publike as a pattern, that all ſpiritual Saylors (if they have no better) may by this imitate themſelves (upon the like occaſions) to raiſe up ſuch Meditations as theſe are.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:61766:55"/>
            <p>
               <hi>REader, I have now ended my Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: I'le conclude my Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If thou by the help of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs arrive the Port, [I mean Heaven] I have my ayme and end; therefore I'le add no more but this: This is my deſired Haven which I ſail unto. And while I ſail, I'le ſing,</hi> Oh that men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and for his wonderfull works to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men! So it is in the Pſalm which I commend to every Saylor to ſtudie and to ſing, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 107.30, 31.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61766:55"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
